<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>HugoGiraudel.com</title>
		<description>I write about front-end development stuff.</description>
		<link>http://hugogiraudel.com</link>
		<atom:link href="http://hugogiraudel.com/feeds/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			
		
			
		
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>Sass-ify a CSS shape</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;section&gt;        &lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;pull-image--right&quot; src=&quot;/images/sass-mixin-star__css-star.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of days ago, &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/thebabydino&quot;&gt;Ana Tudor&lt;/a&gt; showed me how she managed to do a &lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io/thebabydino/pen/DmklE&quot;&gt;pure CSS 6-point star&lt;/a&gt; with a single element.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To be truely honest, I wasn’t impressed that much since I am pretty familiar with Ana’s work which is always amazing. If you haven’t seen &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/users/1397351/ana&quot;&gt;her 3D geometric shapes&lt;/a&gt; made of pure CSS, then you definitely should.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, when I saw this I thought it could be fun to make a &lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io/HugoGiraudel/pen/LkoGE&quot;&gt;Sass version&lt;/a&gt; of it to clean the code and ease the use. Let me show you what I ended up with.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;shape&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Understand the shape &lt;a href=&quot;#shape&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/sass-mixin-star__rhombius.png&quot; class=&quot;pull-image--right&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing was to understand how Ana managed to achieve such a shape with a single element (and 2 pseudo-elements). Long story short:  &lt;strong&gt;chained CSS transforms&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Basically she stacks the element and its 2 pseudo-elements on top of each other after applying several chained transforms to each of them to have the appropriate shape (a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mathopenref.com/rhombus.html&quot;&gt;rhombus&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead of covering everything in here, I let you have a look at &lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io/thebabydino/full/ca5fdb3582a6a27e4d3988d6d90952cb&quot;&gt;this very clear explanation&lt;/a&gt; by Ana herself on CodePen.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;Note: we can do it with one single pseudo-element with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://davidwalsh.name/css-triangles&quot;&gt;border shaping trick&lt;/a&gt; but the hover doesn't feel right, and without pseudo-element with linear gradients.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;compute-the-height&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Compute the height &lt;a href=&quot;#compute-the-height&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I quickly noticed the height and the width of the main element were different. The width is a randomly picked number (10em), but the height seemed to be computed by some calculation since it was 8.66em.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At this point, I was already able to handle a mixin to create the star, but the user had to set both the width and the height. Yet, since the height has to be calculated, it wasn’t right. How is the user supposed to know the appropriate height for the width he set?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The user couldn’t figure this out and neither could I. So I asked Ana how to compute the height of the element based on the width. After a few complicated explanations, she finally gave me the formula (explanation &lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io/thebabydino/full/ca5fdb3582a6a27e4d3988d6d90952cb&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;function computeHeight(x, skewAngle) { 
  return Math.sin((90 - skewAngle) * Math.PI / 180) * x 
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Okay, this is JavaScript but it is a good start. However this returns a radian value, which is not what we want. We want degrees. So the correct function has to be this one:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;function computeHeight(x, skewAngle) { 
  return Math.sin(90 - skewAngle) * x 
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p class=&quot;pull-quote--right&quot;&gt;I had never heard of any &lt;code&gt;sin()&lt;/code&gt; function in Sass.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From there, I knew how to get the height from the width, I only had to turn this into SCSS. First problem: &lt;em&gt;sin()&lt;/em&gt;. I had never heard of any &lt;code&gt;sin()&lt;/code&gt; function in Sass. Damn it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After a little Google search, I stumbled upon &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/adambom/Sass-Math/blob/master/math.scss&quot;&gt;a not-documentated-at-all library&lt;/a&gt; to use advanced math functions in Sass (including &lt;code&gt;sin()&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;exp()&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;sqrt()&lt;/code&gt;, and much more). Seemed good enough so I gave it a try.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It turned out the &lt;code&gt;power()&lt;/code&gt; function (called in the &lt;code&gt;sin()&lt;/code&gt; one) was triggering a Sass error. I tried a few things but finally couldn’t make it work. So I did something unusual... Looked at the 2nd page on Google. And bam, &lt;a href=&quot;http://compass-style.org/reference/compass/helpers/math/&quot;&gt;the Holy Grail&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Compass has built-in functions for advanced math calculation including &lt;code&gt;sin()&lt;/code&gt;. Isn’t that great? Like really awesome? Building the Sass function was a piece of cake:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;@function computeHeight($x, $skewAngle) { 
  @return sin(90deg - $skewAngle) * $x;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This worked like a charm. So &lt;strong&gt;given only the width, Sass was able to calculate the according height.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;units&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Make any unit usable &lt;a href=&quot;#units&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So everything was already working great but I forced the user to give a em-based unit which sucked. I wanted to make any unit available knowing that the &lt;code&gt;computeHeight()&lt;/code&gt; function requires and returns a unitless value. Basically I had to:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;get the value given by the user&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;split it to get both the integer and the unit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;store the unit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pass the integer to the &lt;code&gt;computeHeight()&lt;/code&gt; function&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;get the result&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;apprend the unit to it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had a look in the Sass documentation and I found two related built-in function:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://sass-lang.com/docs/yardoc/Sass/Script/Functions.html#unitless-instance_method&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;unitless(number)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; returns a boolean wether the value has a unit or not&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://sass-lang.com/docs/yardoc/Sass/Script/Functions.html#unit-instance_method&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;unit(number)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; returns the unit of the value&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first is useless in our case, but the second one is precisely what we need to store the unit of the value given by the user. However we still have no way to parse the integer from a value with a unit. At least not with a built-in function. A &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/a/12335841&quot;&gt;quick run on Stack Overflow&lt;/a&gt; gave me what I was looking for:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;You need to divide by 1 of the same unit. If you use unit(), you get a string instead of a number, but if you multiply by zero and add 1, you have what you need:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;pre class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;@function strip-units($number) {
  @return $number / ($number * 0 + 1);
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Do not ask me why it works or how does it work, I have absolutely no idea. This function makes strictly no sense yet it does what we need.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anyway, at this point we can set the size in any unit we want, could it be &lt;code&gt;px&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;rem&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;vh&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;cm&lt;/code&gt;, whatever.
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;improvements&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Improve tiny bits &lt;a href=&quot;#improvements&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, Ana used the &lt;a href=&quot;http://xiel.de/webkit-fix-css-transitions-on-pseudo-elements/&quot;&gt;inherit hack&lt;/a&gt; to enable transition on pseudo-elements. She asked me if we had a way in Sass to assign the same value to several properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course we have, mixin to the rescue!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;@mixin val($properties, $value) {
  @each $prop in $properties {&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#{$prop}:  #{$value};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You give this mixin a &lt;a href=&quot;http://sass-lang.com/docs/yardoc/file.SASS_REFERENCE.html#lists&quot;&gt;list&lt;/a&gt; of properties you want to share the same value and of course the value. Then, for each property in the list, the mixin outputs the given value. In our case:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;:after, &amp;amp;:before {
  $properties: width, height, background;
  @include val($properties, 'inherit');
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... outputs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;.selector:before, .selector:after {
  width      : inherit;
  height     : inherit;
  background : inherit;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s really no big deal. We could totally write those 3 properties/value pairs, but it is great to see what’s possible with Sass, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;code&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Full code &lt;a href=&quot;#code&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the full code for the mixin. As you can see, it is really not that big (especially since Ana's original code is very light).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;@mixin val($properties, $value) {
  @each $prop in $properties {&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#{$prop}: #{$value};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  }
}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;@function computeHeight($x, $skewAngle) {
  @return sin(90deg - $skewAngle) * $x;
}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;@function strip-units($number) {
  @return $number / ($number * 0 + 1);
}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;@mixin star($size) {
  $height: computeHeight(strip-units($size), 30deg);&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  width: $size;
  height: #{$height}#{unit($size)};
  position: relative;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  @include transition(all .3s);
  @include transform(rotate(-30deg) skewX(30deg));&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  &amp;amp;:before,
  &amp;amp;:after {&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$properties: width, height, background;
content: '';
position: absolute;
@include val($properties, 'inherit');
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  }&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  &amp;amp;:before {&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;@include transform(skewX(-30deg) skewX(-30deg)); 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  }
  &amp;amp;:after {&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;@include transform(skewX(-30deg) rotate(-60deg) skewX(-30deg)) 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;final-words&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Final words &lt;a href=&quot;#final-words&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well guys, that’s pretty much it. You have a perfectly working &lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io/HugoGiraudel/pen/LkoGE&quot;&gt;Sass mixin&lt;/a&gt; to create customized single-element 6-point stars in CSS. Pretty neat, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using it couldn't be simpler:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;.star {
  margin: 5em auto;
  background: tomato;
  @include star(10em);&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  &amp;amp;:hover {&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;background: deepskyblue;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks (and congratulations) to &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/thebabydino&quot;&gt;Ana Tudor&lt;/a&gt; for creating such a shape which made me do some cool Sass stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 18 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2013/02/18/sass-mixin-star/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2013/02/18/sass-mixin-star/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>A closer look at my Sass structure</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi guys! Ever since the redesign a few weeks ago I have never stopped trying optimizing the performance of the site. One of my biggest concerns was having a stylesheet which is both nice and efficient.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think I’ve come pretty close to this point thus I thought it might be a good idea to write a bit about it and give you an inside glance at the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Please, consider this post as both a way to introduce some people to Sass and a way to ask Sass experts some advices about the way I handled things. Any comment appreciated. :)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;divide-and-rule&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Divide and rule &lt;a href=&quot;#divide-and-rule&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest problem one faces when building a stylesheet is the size. Depending on the number of pages, elements and templates on your site, you might end up with a huge stylesheet heavy like hell and not so maintainable.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think one of the best things when using a CSS preprocessor -whatever is your cup of tea- is you can split your stylesheets into several parts without risking degrading the performances.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is exactly what I did, spliting my stylesheets into parts. As of writing, I currently have 5 different pieces (5 different .scss files):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;_font-awesome.scss&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;http://fortawesome.github.com/Font-Awesome/&quot;&gt;Font Awesome&lt;/a&gt; is the icon font I use in the site&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;_google-fonts.scss&lt;/code&gt;: this is the snippet from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/webfonts&quot;&gt;Google Web Fonts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;_prism.scss&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;http://prismjs.com/&quot;&gt;Prism.js&lt;/a&gt; is the syntax highlighter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;_helpers.scss&lt;/code&gt;: this file contains my mixins, variables and helper classes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;_styles.scss&lt;/code&gt;: the core of the CSS
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;Note: .scss files starting with a &lt;code&gt;_&lt;/code&gt; are not compiled into .css files.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Since my website isn’t that big, I didn’t have to split the code stylesheet into smaller parts like typography, header, footer, modules, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So basically, my central stylesheet (&lt;code&gt;styles.min.scss&lt;/code&gt; compiled into &lt;code&gt;styles.min.css&lt;/code&gt;) looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;@import &quot;compass/css3/images&quot;;
@import &quot;compass/css3&quot;;

@import &quot;font-awesome&quot;, 
        &quot;google-fonts&quot;, 
        &quot;prism&quot;, 
        &quot;helpers&quot;, 
        &quot;styles&quot;;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first two lines are Compass related imports. It doesn’t compile into the final CSS. They enable use of Compass embedded mixins, sparing me from writing vendor prefixes. The last line imports the 5 files into a single one (top to bottom).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;Note: when importing Sass/SCSS files, you don't need to add underscores or file extensions.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;kiss&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;KISS (Keep It Simple Stupid) &lt;a href=&quot;#kiss&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At first I was using &lt;a href=&quot;http://cssgrid.net&quot;&gt;the 1140px grid&lt;/a&gt; but then it occurred to me I didn’t need a framework as simple as it is to handle a 2-columns layout. I could do it myself and so did I. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My point is: I decided to keep my stylesheet as simple (light) as possible. Thus, I did a huge cleaning in the font-awesome stylesheet. I only kept what was needed: the @font-face call, about ten lines to improve icons position, and the 8 icons I use on the whole site (instead of about 300).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;helpers&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Helpers &lt;a href=&quot;#helpers&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Depending on your project size, you may have various files for that. Maybe one file for variables, one file for mixins, one file for helper classes, and whatever else you like.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My project is fairly (not to say really) small so I gathered everything into a single file. Let’s dig a little bit into it, part by part.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Mixins&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;// Mixin providing a PX fallback for REM font-sizes

@mixin font-size($val) {
    font-size: ($val * 20) + px;
    font-size: $val + rem;
}

// Mixin handling breakpoints for media queries

@mixin breakpoint($point) {
    @if $point == mama-bear {
    @media (max-width: 48em) { @content; }
}
@if $point == baby-bear {
    @media (max-width: 38em) { @content; } 
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Just two. Why having one hundred mixins when you use just two? The first one allows me to use &lt;code&gt;rem&lt;/code&gt; safely for font-size by providing a &lt;code&gt;px&lt;/code&gt; fallback. This is a very nice mixin from Chris Coyier at &lt;a href=&quot;http://css-tricks.com/snippets/css/less-mixin-for-rem-font-sizing/&quot;&gt;CSS-tricks&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second one also comes from &lt;a href=&quot;http://css-tricks.com/media-queries-sass-3-2-and-codekit/&quot;&gt;CSS-tricks&lt;/a&gt; and is a nice way to handle breakpoints for Media Queries within a single MQ declaration. If either I want to change the breakpoints, I don’t have to go through all my stylesheets to find occurrences; all I have to do is edit it in the mixin.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Whenever I want to use a Media Query, I just have to run &lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;@include breakpoint(baby-bear) { /* My stuff here */ }&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;Note: I use &lt;code&gt;em&lt;/code&gt; in media queries in order to prevent some layouts problem when zooming in the browser. More about it in &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.cloudfour.com/the-ems-have-it-proportional-media-queries-ftw/&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; from Lyza Gardner.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Variables&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ah variables. The most awesome thing in any informatic language in the world. This little piece of thing that spare you from repeating again and again the same things. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Native CSS variables are coming but currently only supported by Chrome so meanwhile we rely on CSS preprocessors for variables. I have to say I really didn’t use much in my project. Actually I used 4, not more.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;$pink: #FF3D7F;
$lightgrey: #444;
$mediumgrey: #666;
$darkgrey: #999;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At first I named my variables like &lt;code&gt;$color1&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;$color2&lt;/code&gt;, etc but then it occurred to me I was not able to know what variable I had to set in order to have the right color so I switched back to real color names. It feels easier to me this way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Helper classes&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Helpers are classes you can add to any element to have a quick effect without having to give this element any id or specific class, then set styles and all this stuff.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have quite a few helper classes, some very useful, other a bit less but I use them all in the site. This kind of collection grow up as the project grow so for now it’s kind of small.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's start with the basics:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;%clearfix&lt;/code&gt; is an invisible class meant to be extended (@extend) to clear floats in an element containing only floated elements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;.icon-left&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;.icon-right&lt;/code&gt; are used on inline icons to prevent them from sticking the text&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;%clearfix {
    &amp;:after {
        display: table;
        content: &quot;&quot;;
        clear: both 
    }
}

.icon-left { margin-right: 5px }
.icon-right { margin-left: 5px }&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;




&lt;p&gt;Then, two helpers to give content specific meaning:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;.visually-hidden&lt;/code&gt; simply make the text disappear while keeping it accessible for both screen readers and search engine bots.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;.note&lt;/code&gt; is used to tell a paragraph is a note which could be removed without affecting the sense of the content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;.visually-hidden { 
    position: absolute; 
    overflow: hidden; 
    clip: rect(0 0 0 0); 
    height: 1px; width: 1px; 
    margin: -1px; 
    padding: 0; 
    border: none; 
}

.note {
    font-style: italic;
    padding-left: 1em;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And now let's dig into more interesting stuff. I have built some useful classes to pull images or quotes out of the flow and put them on the side in order to emphasize them. Both are built in the same way:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;%pull-quote&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;%pull-image&lt;/code&gt; are invisible classes; it means they won’t be compiled in the stylesheet, they are only here to be extended&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;.pull-quote--left&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;.pull-quote--right&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;.pull-image--left&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;.pull-image--right&lt;/code&gt; respectively inherit (&lt;code&gt;@extend&lt;/code&gt;) styles from &lt;code&gt;%pull-quote&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;%pull-image&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Plus, they have some specific styles like margins, float, borders, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;On small screens, they are not floated any more, pulled back in the flow and centered&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;%pull-image {
    max-width: 15em;
    display: block;

    @include breakpoint(baby-bear) { 
        float: none;
        width: 100%;
        margin: 1em auto;
    }
}

.pull-image--left {
    @extend %pull-image;
    float: left;
    margin: 0 1em 1em 0;
}

.pull-image--right {
    @extend %pull-image;
    float: right;
    margin: 0 0 1em 1em;
}

%pull-quote {
    max-width: 250px;
    width: 100%;
    position: relative;
    line-height: 1.35;
    font-size: 1.5em;

    &amp;:after,
    &amp;:before {
        content: '&quot;';
        font-family: Times New Roman, serif;
    }

    @include breakpoint(baby-bear) { 
        float: none;
        margin: 1em auto;
        border: 5px solid $pink;
        border-left: none;
        border-right: none;
        text-align: center;
        padding: 1em 0.5em;
        max-width: 100%;
    }
}

.pull-quote--left {
    @extend %pull-quote;
    text-align: right;
    float: left;
    padding-right: 1em;
    margin: 0 1em 0 0;
    border-right: 6px solid $pink;
}

.pull-quote--right {
    @extend %pull-quote;
    text-align: left;
    float: right;
    padding-left: 1em;
    margin: 0 0 0 1em;
    border-left: 6px solid $pink;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Please note how I nest media queries inside their related selectors. There are two main reasons for this:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This makes the stylesheet easier to maintain since you have everything at the same place: regular rules + conditional rules. No need of going at the bottom of the stylesheet to find all the conditional CSS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When compiling, Sass doesn’t generate a bunch of media queries but a single one. So no performance issue on this point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;Note: if you ever wonder about the double dashes or underscores in class names, it is related to the BEM (Block Element Modifier) approach. More on the topic in &lt;a href=&quot;http://csswizardry.com/2013/01/mindbemding-getting-your-head-round-bem-syntax/&quot;&gt;this excellent post&lt;/a&gt; from Harry Roberts.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;core&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Core of styles&lt;a href=&quot;#core&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now we’ve seen pretty much everything else than what makes the site what it is, I think it’s time to dig into the main stylesheet. For reading concern I’ll split it into several code snippets here. Plus it will be easier for commenting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Reset&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is not optional, every project needs to use some kind of way to reset CSS styles. Depending on your tastes it might be &lt;a href=&quot;http://meyerweb.com/eric/tools/css/reset/&quot;&gt;Eric Meyer’s CSS reset&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://necolas.github.com/normalize.css/&quot;&gt;Normalize CSS&lt;/a&gt; or as I like to call it the &lt;strong&gt;barbarian CSS&lt;/strong&gt; as below.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;*,
*:before,
*:after {
    @include box-sizing(border-box);
    padding: 0;
    margin: 0;
}
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes I know, this is dirty. I shouldn’t not reset CSS this way but honestly on small projects like this, it’s really not a big deal. At first I used Normalize CSS but then I realized loading kilobytes of code when 2 lines are enough is not necessary. So barbarian CSS reset guys!&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please note I use the simplest box-sizing since IE (all versions) represents less than 1.5% of my traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Overall stuff&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn’t really know how to call this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;html {&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;font: 20px/1 &quot;HelveticaNeue-Light&quot;,&quot;Helvetica Neue Light&quot;,&quot;Helvetica Neue&quot;,&quot;Helvetica&quot;,&quot;Arial&quot;,&quot;Lucida Grande&quot;,sans-serif;
color: #555;
text-shadow: 0 1px rgba(255,255,255,0.6);

border-left: 6px solid $pink;
background-image: url(&quot;data:image/png;base64,hErEiSaFuCkInGlOnGdAtAuRiaSaBaCkGrOuNd&quot;);

@include breakpoint(baby-bear) { 
    border-left: none;
    border-top: 5px solid $pink;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a {&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;color: $pink;
text-decoration: none;

&amp;amp;:hover {
    text-decoration: underline;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basic stuff here. Font-size, color, font-families, text-shadows and everything that needs to cascade on the whole document are set on the root element (&lt;code&gt;html&lt;/code&gt;). I also give a little custom styles to anchor tags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Containers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This used to be in the 1140px stylesheet but since I don’t use anymore, I moved it back here. It’s all about main wrappers and containers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;.row {&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;width: 100%;
max-width: 57em;
margin: 0 auto;
padding: 0 1em;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;.main {&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;@extend %content;
width: 68%;
margin-right: 2%;

@include breakpoint(mama-bear) { 
    margin-right: 0;
    border-bottom: 3px solid #D1D1D1;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;.sidebar {&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;@extend %content;
width: 30%;
padding-top: 2em;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;%content {&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;padding-bottom: 3em;
float: left;

@include breakpoint(mama-bear) {
    float: none;
    width: 100%;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;}&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;.row&lt;/code&gt; is the main wrapper: it contains the header, the main column (&lt;code&gt;.main&lt;/code&gt;), the sidebar (&lt;code&gt;.sidebar&lt;/code&gt;) and the footer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;.content&lt;/code&gt; is an invisible shared class between both the main column and the sidebar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;final-words&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Final words &lt;a href=&quot;#final-words&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I deliberately skipped the rest of the stylesheet since I think it's not the most interesting part in my opinion. It mostly consists on setting styles for various content elements like paragraphs, lists, tables, images, titles, and so on. Plus, it's classic CSS, not really SCSS magic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I have covered most of my Sass structure. If you feel like something could be improved or if you have any question, please be sure to drop a comment. :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2013/02/11/sass-structure/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2013/02/11/sass-structure/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>Dig deep into CSS linear gradients</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following is a guest post by &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/thebabydino&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;Ana Tudor&lt;/a&gt;. She is passionate about experimenting and learning new things. Also she loves maths and enjoys playing with code.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/css-gradients__rainbow_wheel_screen.gif&quot; class=&quot;pull-image--right&quot; alt=&quot;Rainbow wheel&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had no idea how powerful CSS gradients could be until late 2011, when I found the &lt;a href=&quot;http://lea.verou.me/css3patterns/&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;CSS3 Patterns Gallery&lt;/a&gt; made by Lea Verou. The idea that you can obtain many shapes using just gradients was a starting point for many CSS experiments I would later do.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Recently, while browsing through the demos on CodePen, I came across &lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io/bitmap/pen/eBbHt&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;a CSS3 Color Wheel&lt;/a&gt; and thought &lt;q&gt;hey, I could do it with just one element and gradients&lt;/q&gt;. So I did and the result can be seen &lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io/thebabydino/pen/hkxGp&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. And now I'm going to explain the reasoning behind it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;breaking-it-down&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Breaking it down &lt;a href=&quot;#breaking-it-down&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The wheel - or you can think of it as a pie - is first split horizontally into two halves and then each half is split into five slices, so there are ten slices in total. Which means that the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central_angle&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;central angle&lt;/a&gt; for each slice is &lt;code&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mathopenref.com/degrees.html&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;360°&lt;/a&gt;/10 = 36°&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The pen below shows graphically how to layer the multiple backgrounds. It also has a pause button so that the infinite animation doesn't turn into a performance problem.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre class=&quot;codepen&quot; data-height=&quot;340&quot; data-type=&quot;result&quot; data-href=&quot;Kuvom&quot; data-user=&quot;thebabydino&quot; data-safe=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For both the original pen and this helper demo, the interesting part is this one:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre class=&quot; language-css&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;background: 
linear-gradient(36deg, #272b66 42.34%, transparent 42.34%),
linear-gradient(72deg, #2d559f 75.48%, transparent 75.48%),
linear-gradient(-36deg, #9ac147 42.34%, transparent 42.34%) 100% 0,
linear-gradient(-72deg, #639b47 75.48%, transparent 75.48%) 100% 0, 
linear-gradient(36deg, transparent 57.66%, #e1e23b 57.66%) 100% 100%,
linear-gradient(72deg, transparent 24.52%, #f7941e 24.52%) 100% 100%,
linear-gradient(-36deg, transparent 57.66%, #662a6c 57.66%) 0 100%,
linear-gradient(-72deg, transparent 24.52%, #9a1d34 24.52%) 0 100%, 
#43a1cd linear-gradient(#ba3e2e, #ba3e2e) 50% 100%;
background-repeat: no-repeat;
background-size: 50% 50%;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We first specify the nine gradient backgrounds, their positioning and the &lt;code&gt;background-color&lt;/code&gt; using the shorthand &lt;code&gt;background&lt;/code&gt; syntax.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;background-shorthand&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The background shorthand &lt;a href=&quot;#background-shorthand&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For anyone who doesn't remember, the background layers are listed from the top one to the bottom one and the &lt;code&gt;background-color&lt;/code&gt; is specified together with the bottom layer. A background layer includes the following:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;background-image&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;background-position&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; / &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;background-size&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;background-repeat&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;background-attachment&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;background-origin&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;background-clip&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If the &lt;code&gt;background-position&lt;/code&gt; is not specified, then the &lt;code&gt;background-size&lt;/code&gt; isn't specified either. Also, since &lt;code&gt;background-origin&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;background-clip&lt;/code&gt; both need the same kind of value (that is, a box value like &lt;code&gt;border-box&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;content-box&lt;/code&gt;), then, if there is only one such value, that value is given to both &lt;code&gt;background-origin&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;background-clip&lt;/code&gt;. Other than that, any value except the one for &lt;code&gt;background-image&lt;/code&gt; can be missing and then it is assumed to be the default.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Since we have nine background layers and we want to have the same non-default values for &lt;code&gt;background-repeat&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;background-size&lt;/code&gt; for all of them, we specify these outside the shorthand so that we don't have to write the same thing nine times.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p class=&quot;pull-quote--right&quot;&gt;Safari doesn't support background-size inside the shorthand.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the case of &lt;code&gt;background-size&lt;/code&gt;, there is also another reason to do that: Safari doesn't support &lt;code&gt;background-size&lt;/code&gt; inside the shorthand and, until recently (up to and including version 17), Firefox didn't support that either. Also, two values should be always given when the &lt;code&gt;background-image&lt;/code&gt; is a gradient, because giving it just one value is going to produce different results in different browsers (unless that one value is 100%, in which case it might as well be missing as that is the default).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;background-color&lt;/code&gt; is set to be a light blue (&lt;code&gt;#43a1cd&lt;/code&gt;) and then, on top of it, there are layered nine non-repeating (&lt;code&gt;background-repeat: no-repeat&lt;/code&gt; for all) background images created using CSS gradients. All nine of them are half the &lt;code&gt;width&lt;/code&gt; and the &lt;code&gt;height&lt;/code&gt; of the element (&lt;code&gt;background-size: 50% 50%&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The bottom one - horizontally centred (&lt;code&gt;50%&lt;/code&gt;) and at the bottom (&lt;code&gt;100%&lt;/code&gt;) - is really simple. It's just a gradient from a firebrick red to the same color (&lt;code&gt;linear-gradient(#ba3e2e, #ba3e2e)&lt;/code&gt;), so the result is simply a solid color square.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The other eight are gradients from &lt;code&gt;transparent&lt;/code&gt; to a solid color or from a solid color to &lt;code&gt;transparent&lt;/code&gt;. Four of them look like double slices, having a central angle of &lt;code&gt;2*36° = 72°&lt;/code&gt;, but half of each such double slice gets covered by another single slice (having a central angle of &lt;code&gt;36°&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;about-linear-gradients&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;A few things about linear gradients &lt;a href=&quot;#about-linear-gradients&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In order to better understand gradient angles and how the &lt;code&gt;%&lt;/code&gt; values for color stops are computed, let's see how a linear gradient is defined. Hopefully, this demo that lets you change the gradient angle helps with that - just click the dots.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre class=&quot;codepen&quot; data-height=&quot;640&quot; data-type=&quot;result&quot; data-href=&quot;qgoBL&quot; data-user=&quot;thebabydino&quot; data-safe=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io/thebabydino/pen/qgoBL&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;Check out this Pen!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;gradient angle&lt;/em&gt; is the angle - measured clockwise - between the vertical axis and the &lt;em&gt;gradient line&lt;/em&gt; (the blue line in the demo). This is for the new syntax, which is not yet supported by WebKit browsers (however, &lt;a href=&quot;https://bugs.webkit.org/show_bug.cgi?id=67166&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;this is going to change&lt;/a&gt;). The old syntax measured angles just like on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unit_circle&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;trigonometric unit circle&lt;/a&gt; (counter-clockwise and starting from the horizontal axis).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;Note: coming from a mathematical background, I have to say the old way feels more natural to me. However, the new way feels consistent with other CSS features, like rotate transforms, for which the angle values are also clockwise.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What this means is that we (almost always) have different angle values in the standard syntax and in the current WebKit syntax. So, if we are not using something like &lt;a href=&quot;http://leaverou.github.com/prefixfree/&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;-prefix-free&lt;/a&gt; (which I do almost all the time), then we should to be able to compute one when knowing the other. That is actually pretty simple. They are going in opposite directions, so the formula for one includes the other with a minus sign. Also, there is a &lt;code&gt;90°&lt;/code&gt; difference between them so this is how we get them: &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;newSyntax = 90° - oldSyntax;
oldSyntax = 90° - newSyntax;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;Note: if no gradient angle or destination side is specified (for example, &lt;code&gt;linear-gradient(lime, yellow)&lt;/code&gt;), then the resulting gradient is going to have a gradient angle of &lt;code&gt;180°&lt;/code&gt;, not &lt;code&gt;0°&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All the points on a line that is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mathopenref.com/perpendicular.html&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;perpendicular&lt;/a&gt; on the gradient line have the same color. The perpendicular from the corner in the quadrant that's opposite to the quadrant of the angle is the &lt;code&gt;0%&lt;/code&gt; line (the crimson line in the demo) and its intersection with the gradient line is the &lt;em&gt;starting point&lt;/em&gt; of the gradient (let's call it &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;S&lt;/code&gt;). The perpendicular from the opposite corner (the one in the same quadrant as the gradient angle) is the &lt;code&gt;100%&lt;/code&gt; line (the black line in the demo) and its intersection with the gradient line is the &lt;em&gt;ending point&lt;/em&gt; of the gradient (let's call it &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;E&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/css-gradients__gradient.png&quot; alt=&quot;Gradient with gradient line, 0% line, 100% line&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to compute the &lt;code&gt;%&lt;/code&gt; value of any point &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;P&lt;/code&gt;, we first draw a perpendicular on the gradient line starting from that point. The intersection between the gradient line and this perpendicular is going to be a point we'll name &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;I&lt;/code&gt;. We now compute the ratio between the lengths of &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;SI&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;SE&lt;/code&gt; and the &lt;code&gt;%&lt;/code&gt; value for that point is going to be &lt;code&gt;100%&lt;/code&gt; times that ratio.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;putting-it-all-to-work&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Putting it all to work &lt;a href=&quot;#putting-it-all-to-work&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now let's see how we apply this for the particular case of the rainbow wheel.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's first consider a gradient that creates a single slice (one with a central angle of &lt;code&gt;36°&lt;/code&gt;). This is a square image (see below), with a blue slice having an angle of &lt;code&gt;36°&lt;/code&gt; in the lower part. We draw the horizontal and vertical axes through the point &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;O&lt;/code&gt; at which the diagonals intersect. We draw a perpendicular from that point to the line that separates the dark blue part from the transparent part. This is going to be the gradient line. As it can be seen, there is a &lt;code&gt;36°&lt;/code&gt; angle between the vertical axis and the gradient line, so the angle of the gradient is &lt;code&gt;36°&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/css-gradients__slice_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Applying the theory for the first slice&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now draw a perpendicular from the corner of the square in the quadrant that is opposite to the one in which the gradient angle is found. This is the &lt;code&gt;0%&lt;/code&gt; line. Then we draw a perpendicular from the corner of the square in the same quadrant (&lt;code&gt;Q I&lt;/code&gt;) as the gradient angle - this is the &lt;code&gt;100%&lt;/code&gt; line.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mathopenref.com/square.html&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;intersection of the diagonals of a square splits each one of them into two&lt;/a&gt;, so &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;AO&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;BO&lt;/code&gt; are equal. The &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;BOE&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;AOS&lt;/code&gt; angles are equal, as they are &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mathopenref.com/anglesvertical.html&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;vertical angles&lt;/a&gt;. Moreover, the &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;BOE&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;AOS&lt;/code&gt; triangles are &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mathopenref.com/righttriangle.html&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;right triangles&lt;/a&gt;. All these three &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triangle#Similarity_and_congruence&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;mean that the two triangles are also congruent&lt;/a&gt;. Which in turn means that &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;SO&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;EO&lt;/code&gt; are equal, so the length of &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;SE&lt;/code&gt; is going to be twice the length of &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;EO&lt;/code&gt; or twice the length of &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;SO&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/css-gradients__right_triangle_trigonometric_functions.png&quot; class=&quot;pull-image--right&quot; alt=&quot;A right angled triangle and how to compute sime and cosine functions&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;Note: before moving further, let's go through a couple of trigonometry concepts first. The longest side of a right-angled triangle is the one opposing that right angle and it's called the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mathopenref.com/hypotenuse.html&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;hypotenuse&lt;/a&gt;. The other two sides (the ones forming the right angle) are called the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cathetus&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;catheti&lt;/a&gt; of the right triangle. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mathopenref.com/sine.html&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;sine&lt;/a&gt; of an acute angle in a right triangle is the ratio between the cathetus opposing that angle and the hypotenuse. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mathopenref.com/cosine.html&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;cosine&lt;/a&gt; of the same angle is the ratio between the adjacent cathetus and the hypothenuse.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/css-gradients__slice_1_BOE.png&quot; class=&quot;pull-image--right&quot; alt=&quot;The BOE triangle&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computing the length of &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;EO&lt;/code&gt; in the right triangle &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;BOE&lt;/code&gt; is really simple. If we take the length of the side of the square to be &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;a&lt;/code&gt;, then the length of the half diagonal &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;BO&lt;/code&gt; is going to be &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;a*sqrt(2)/2&lt;/code&gt;. The &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;BOE&lt;/code&gt; angle is equal to the difference between the &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;BOM&lt;/code&gt; angle, which is &lt;code&gt;45°&lt;/code&gt;, and the &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;EOM&lt;/code&gt; angle, which is &lt;code&gt;36°&lt;/code&gt;. This makes &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;BOE&lt;/code&gt; have &lt;code&gt;9°&lt;/code&gt;. Since &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;BO&lt;/code&gt; is also the hypotenuse in the right triangle &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;BOE&lt;/code&gt;, the length of &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;EO&lt;/code&gt; is going to be &lt;code&gt;(&lt;span class='var'&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;*sqrt(2)/2)*cos9°&lt;/code&gt;. Which makes the length of &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;SE&lt;/code&gt; be &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;a*sqrt(2)*cos9°&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/css-gradients__slice_1_APD.png&quot; class=&quot;pull-image--right&quot; alt=&quot;The APD triangle&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now draw a perpendicular from &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;A&lt;/code&gt; to the &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;PI&lt;/code&gt; line. &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;ASID&lt;/code&gt; is a rectangle, which means that the length of &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;SI&lt;/code&gt; equals the length of &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;AD&lt;/code&gt;. We now consider the rectangular triangle &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;APD&lt;/code&gt;. In this triangle, &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;AP&lt;/code&gt; is the hypotenuse and has a length of &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;a&lt;/code&gt;. This means that &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;AD&lt;/code&gt; is going to have a length of &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;a*sin36°&lt;/code&gt;. But &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;SI&lt;/code&gt; is equal to &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;AD&lt;/code&gt;, so it also has a length of &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;a*sin36°&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Since we now know both &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;SI&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;var&quot;&gt;SE&lt;/code&gt;, we can compute their ratio. It is &lt;code&gt;sin36°/(sqrt(2)*cos9°) = 0.4234&lt;/code&gt;. So the &lt;code&gt;%&lt;/code&gt; value for the color stop is &lt;code&gt;42.34%&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this way, we've arrived at: &lt;code&gt;linear-gradient(36deg, #272b66 42.34%, transparent 42.34%)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Computing the &lt;code&gt;%&lt;/code&gt; values for the other background layers is done in the exact same manner.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;automating&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Automating all this &lt;a href=&quot;#automating&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;By now, you're probably thinking it sucks to do so many computations. And it must be even worse when there are more gradients with different angles...&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even though for creating the rainbow wheel experiment I did compute everything on paper... I can only agree with that! This is why I made a really basic little tool that computes the &lt;code&gt;%&lt;/code&gt; for any point inside the gradient box. You just need to click inside it and the &lt;code&gt;%&lt;/code&gt; value appears in a box at the bottom center.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre class=&quot;codepen&quot; data-height=&quot;320&quot; data-type=&quot;result&quot; data-href=&quot;FDbdB&quot; data-user=&quot;thebabydino&quot; data-safe=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io/thebabydino/pen/FDbdB&quot;&gt;Check out this Pen!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can change the dimensions of the gradient box and you can also change the gradient itself. It accepts the newest syntax for linear gradients, with angle values in degrees, &lt;code&gt;to &amp;lt;side&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; values or no value at all for describing the direction of the gradient.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;final-words&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Final words &lt;a href=&quot;#final-words&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;CSS gradients are really powerful and understanding how they work can be really useful for creating all sorts of imageless textures or shapes that would be difficult to obtain otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.gravatar.com/avatar/bee436794e066a5423040cf673c7506f?s=200&quot; alt=&quot;Ana Tudor's gravatar&quot; class=&quot;pull-image--left&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ana Tudor excels in CSS, especially when it comes to CSS transforms and well, as you may have seen, CSS gradients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You definitely should follow her on &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/thebabydino&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; or have a look at &lt;a href=&quot;http://about.me/thebabydino&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;her profile&lt;/a&gt; to know more about her and what she does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script async src=&quot;http://codepen.io/assets/embed/ei.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2013/02/04/css-gradients/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2013/02/04/css-gradients/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>Simulate float: down</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in september, some guy exposed a very interesting problem on &lt;a href=&quot;http://css-tricks.com/forums/discussion/19610/float-items&quot;&gt;CSS-tricks forums&lt;/a&gt;. To sum up, he had a list of elements floated to the left. However, he wanted to float items top to bottom on each column and not left to right on each row.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;He started with:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://img401.imageshack.us/img401/4723/98791854.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And wanted to end with:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://imageshack.us/scaled/landing/88/51843399.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;solutions&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Solutions to the problem&lt;a href=&quot;#solutions&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Flexbox&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even if I'm not a flexbox expert, I'm pretty confident saying there is a way to do it very easily. The problem with flexbox is that it's not fully compatible so we had to look for another option.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Actually &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/bennettfeely&quot;&gt;Bennett Feely&lt;/a&gt; did it very nicely already on &lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io/bennettfeely/pen/firxL&quot;&gt;CodePen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Manually&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I first managed to do it with &lt;code&gt;:nth-child()&lt;/code&gt; selectors, replacing manually each one of the ten elements (&lt;a href=&quot;http://jsfiddle.net/VAdT3/1/&quot;&gt;JSFiddle&lt;/a&gt;). It sucked because it was:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manual,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dependant of the number of items,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CSS heavy,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not elegant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;JavaScript&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was very upset not finding any proper way to do it with CSS so I did it with a mix of CSS and JavaScript (in fact jQuery). I don't know if it's the best way to do it in JavaScript but here is what I came up with:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;$('.myList &gt; li:odd').remove().appendTo('.myList');&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Basically I target one out of two items with &lt;code&gt;:nth-child(even)&lt;/code&gt; then remove it from the DOM to finally append it again. This does exactly what was asked so I think it's a decent solution (&lt;a href=&quot;http://jsfiddle.net/VAdT3/6/&quot;&gt;JSFiddle&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Margins&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally someone came up with a better idea (and probably a better understanding of CSS) than mine with a pure CSS and very elegant solution (&lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io/wolfcry911/pen/IkBbu&quot;&gt;CodePen&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;li:nth-child(even) {
    margin: 110px 0 0 -110px; 
    /* Given a 100*100px element with a 10px margin */
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Wolfcry911 simply used margins to reposition one out of two items. It's a brilliant solution, really.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;However it relies on CSS advanced pseudo-selectors so for a deeper browser support, you might want get back to the JavaScript solution.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Columns (edit 31/01/2013)&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I just noticed &lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io/estelle&quot;&gt;Estelle Weyl&lt;/a&gt; did it in another clever way with CSS columns (&lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io/estelle/pen/zkjrn&quot;&gt;CodePen&lt;/a&gt;). I'm actually wondering if it's not the better option all in all since it requires only one single CSS line (prefixes omitted).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;ul {
    columns: 5;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to her for such a smart solution. :)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;moar&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Pushing it further&lt;a href=&quot;#moar&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, Chris Coyier found Wolfcry911's work and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/chriscoyier/status/295223893516500993&quot;&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt; about it. Someone (in the person of &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/arashmilan&quot;&gt;Arash Milani&lt;/a&gt;) answered it wasn't possible to do it with more than 2 rows.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CHALLENGE ACCEPTED!&lt;/strong&gt; This made me want to give it a shot. Honestly, it took me a few tries and no more than 10 minutes to find a solution for 3 rows.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;codepen&quot; data-height=&quot;450&quot; data-type=&quot;result&quot; data-href=&quot;DoAIB&quot; data-user=&quot;HugoGiraudel&quot; data-safe=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io/HugoGiraudel/pen/DoAIB&quot;&gt;Check out this Pen!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead of doing &lt;code&gt;:nth-child(even)&lt;/code&gt;, we need two different selectors:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;li:nth-child(3n+2){
    margin: 120px 0 0 -110px;
    background: limegreen;
}

li:nth-child(3n+3) {
    margin: 230px 0 0 -110px;
    background: crimson;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;sass&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Automating the process&lt;a href=&quot;#sass&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I found a solution to do it with the number of rows we want, pretty cool. Immediately, I thought about automating this. And guess what? I succeeded.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Prepare the ground&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First, I had to move everything to em units in order to make the whole thing easier to customize. I also created a few variables:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;$rows: 4; 
$baseline: 10px;
$width: 4em;
$height: 4em;
$margin: 0.4em;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A few explanations about the variables:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;$rows&lt;/code&gt; stands for the number of rows you want,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;$baseline&lt;/code&gt; is set as a font-size to the root element (&lt;code&gt;html&lt;/code&gt;) in order to be able to use em everywhere,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;$width&lt;/code&gt; is the width of each item; in my demo it equals 100px,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;$height&lt;/code&gt; is the height of each item; in my demo it equals 100px as well,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;$margin&lt;/code&gt; is the gap between each item; I set it to 10% of the size of an item.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;Note: you may wonder why using 2 different variables for size when one would be enough. This allows you to use non-square items if you want to: try it, it works.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Looping!&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now let's get to the funny part. I figured out there is some kind of pattern to achieve this and to be honest it took me a while (no pun intended) to create the while loop for this, struggling between my comprehension of the problem and Sass syntax errors. Anyway, this is the main idea:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;$i: $rows; // Initializing the loop

@while $i &amp;gt; 1 {

    li:nth-child(#{$rows}n+#{$i}) {
        $j: $i - 1; // Setting a $i-1 variable

        margin-top: $j * $height + $i * $margin;
        margin-left: -($width + $margin);
    }

    $i: $i - 1;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is pretty tough. Let me show you how it compiles when $rows is set to 4 (other variables remain unchanged):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;li:nth-child(4n+4) {
    margin-top: 13.6em;  // (3 * 4em) + (4 * 0.4em)
    margin-left: -4.4em; // -(4em + 0.4em)
}

li:nth-child(4n+3) {
    margin-top: 9.2em;   // (2 * 4em) + (3 * 0.4em)
    margin-left: -4.4em; // -(4em + 0.4em)
}

li:nth-child(4n+2) {
    margin-top: 4.8em;   // (1 * 4em) + (2 * 0.4em)
    margin-left: -4.4em; // -(4em + 0.4em)
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I think the pattern should be easier to see now thanks to the comments. For X rows you'll have &lt;code&gt;X-1&lt;/code&gt; different selectors starting from &lt;code&gt;:nth-child(Xn+Y)&lt;/code&gt; (where X and Y are the same) until Y becomes stricly superior than 1 (so Y equals 2).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;demo&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Demo&lt;a href=&quot;#demo&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;pre class=&quot;codepen&quot; data-height=&quot;530&quot; data-type=&quot;result&quot; data-href=&quot;AxmBK&quot; data-user=&quot;HugoGiraudel&quot; data-safe=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io/HugoGiraudel/pen/AxmBK&quot;&gt;Check out this Pen!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Try changing the number of rows by editing &lt;code&gt;$rows&lt;/code&gt; and see the magic happen.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;final-words&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Final words&lt;a href=&quot;#final-words&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are still some problems with this method like: what if items have various sizes? Or what if we want different margins? Or what if we set a disproportionate number of rows given the number of items?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I guess we could complicate the whole thing to accept more parameters and be even more flexible but would it worth it? I guess not. &lt;strong&gt;The simple way is to use JavaScript. The funny way is to use Sass.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script async src=&quot;http://codepen.io/assets/embed/ei.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2013/01/28/float-down/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2013/01/28/float-down/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>My development environment</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hey guys! I recently blogged about the tools I use for front-end development, but someone pointed out on Twitter I didn't tell anything about my development environment. Let's fix my mistake and talk about it!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, first of all, it is kind of complicated because I work at 3 different places, which means I have 3 different development environments (5 actually, I have 3 computers at home). There is -well- home, but I also happen to do some stuff at school or at work when I have some time, mostly during the lunch break.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I will try to describe what I use to work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;os&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Operating system&lt;a href=&quot;#os&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's start with the easy thing: the operating system. First, &lt;strong&gt;I use both Mac and Windows&lt;/strong&gt;. At home, I mostly use my girlfriend's laptop which is a 4-year old Mac. I also have 2 computers I use(d) for gaming which runs Windows 7 and Windows Vista.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At work, I am on Windows XP. Yeah, that's not cool, I know. But the whole infrastructure is based on Windows XP, so even developers work stations are using XP. Anyway, I can live with it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At school we're on Windows 7. The computers there are pretty cool I must say.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I didn't try Linux yet but I think I might come to it sooner or later. I like challenge.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;browser&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Browser&lt;a href=&quot;#browser&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ah, browsers. Our main tools. For the record, not so long ago I swear only by Firefox. But when I started doing a lot of stuff on the web at the same time (running many tabs with somewhat heavy content like videos, WebGL, CSS animations, etc.), it occurred to me Firefox was suffering from a bad memory management. Which wasn't the case of Chrome.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I switched to Chrome and never looked back. I even pushed it one step further, using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/intl/en/chrome/browser/canary.html&quot;&gt;Chrome Canary&lt;/a&gt;. This in order to access to a few things Chrome doesn't support (or didn't support at the time I switched to Canary) like CSS shaders, exclusions, regions and so on.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p class=&quot;pull-quote--right&quot;&gt;I don't dislike Firefox -it's a wonderful browser- but I clearly prefer Chrome.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At work for something which looks like SSL issue, I am also running &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mozilla.org/fr/firefox/channel/&quot;&gt;Firefox Aurora&lt;/a&gt; which is the future version of Firefox, like Canary for Chrome. I don't dislike Firefox -it's a wonderful browser- but I clearly prefer Chrome.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I also have Opera and Safari on some computers to make unusual tests. Since I am not a freelance web designer living from the sites I make, I'm not using any browser testing tool like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.browserstack.com/&quot;&gt;BrowserStack&lt;/a&gt;. I would really love a BrowserStack license, but I can't (or don't want to) afford a $20/month subscription.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;ide&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;IDE&lt;a href=&quot;#ide&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/development-environment__sublime-text.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sublime Text 2&quot; class=&quot;pull-image--right&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to be a huge fan of Notepad++, even if everybody was using Dreamweaver. Honestly I never liked DW; it is super heavy while doing not much than a regular text editor.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now I am standing on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sublimetext.com/2&quot;&gt;Sublime Text 2&lt;/a&gt; on all my computers, with no intention to change soon. The thing Sublime Text 2 provides that Notepad++ doesn't is the ability to open a whole folder in order to have access to any file of your project in the arborescence. This is really cool. Plus Sublime Text 2 looks better in my opinion. :)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That being said, I'm carefully looking into &lt;a href=&quot;http://brackets.io/&quot;&gt;Brackets&lt;/a&gt; from Adobe which is a web-based IDE looking pretty cool.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;ftp&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;FTP&lt;a href=&quot;#ftp&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Call me old fashioned, I do still use a FTP client. Yes, I know it's not 2000' anymore but I don't know how to use FTP from the command line, so I am stuck with a &lt;a href=&quot;http://filezilla-project.org/&quot;&gt;FileZilla&lt;/a&gt;. It is actually pretty cool and very easy to use.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;However I would like to move forward, thus I am currently learning how to do some FTP stuff through the command line but I'm still not very good at it so for now I keep using my beloved FileZilla.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Design&lt;a href=&quot;#design&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, I am a huge fan of this &lt;strong&gt;design in the browser&lt;/strong&gt; thing, plus I am very sucky when it comes to any designing tool. I mean you, Photoshop. So really, I hardly use Photoshop, unless I am forced to.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;However I have the good luck to have an Adobe Creative Suite on most of my development workflows. Work provides official liences, we have student licences at school and I have a student licence at home as well.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You may find this silly but 9 out of 10 times, I use Photoshop to resize and save a screenshot I just took. Yeah... A $3000 software to make screenshots is a bit expensive I guess.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;tools&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Other tools&lt;a href=&quot;#tools&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I didn't know how to call this section because it gathers various tools doing various things I use at various occasions. I hope it's clear enough. :P&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Sass &amp;amp; Compass&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/development-environment__sass-compass.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sass and Compass&quot; class=&quot;pull-image--right&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not so long ago I gave a try to CSS preprocessors, because I am both curious and a CSS lover. It turned out I like CSS preprocessors, they give a lot more options than regular CSS.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I am using &lt;a href=&quot;http://sass-lang.com/&quot;&gt;Sass&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://compass-style.org/&quot;&gt;Compass&lt;/a&gt; on most of my projects now. As an example, this site is built on Sass.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am running Sass through the command line. Yes, it's scary. But actually it is really not that hard. I would like to have some sort of application taking care of everything for me like &lt;a href=&quot;http://incident57.com/codekit/&quot;&gt;CodeKit&lt;/a&gt;, unfortunately I am not always on Mac OS plus CodeKit is not free ($25). If I was always using the same development environment, I would definitely buy CodeKit but sadly I am not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I know there are CodeKit equivalents for Windows. Most people will tell you about &lt;a href=&quot;http://mhs.github.com/scout-app/&quot;&gt;Scout&lt;/a&gt;. I tried it yesterday (as I told you I am curious). Guess what: it turns out Scout was messing with my stylesheets, introducing errors in those. My opinion about it? It sucks. Back to command line.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Git&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yaaaaay! Git, my dear friend! Guys, &lt;strong&gt;I suck at Git&lt;/strong&gt;. I understand the main idea, I even know how to do some very basic stuff but every single time I need to do something it takes me about 20 minutes, I have to try every command I know (which is about 6 or 7), fail, get upset, read the doc, don't understand anything either and finally ask my brother. Long story short, I don't like Git... yet.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But I still have an &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/HugoGiraudel&quot;&gt;account at GitHub&lt;/a&gt; which only has 2 repositories as of today (good ones tho!). I hope I'll push other things in the not so distand future.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Local server&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I have to do some server side stuff, mostly PHP (sometimes MySQL), I use EasyPHP when I'm on a Windows machine or Mamp when I'm on Mac.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;final-words&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Final words&lt;a href=&quot;#final-words&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well I guess I have covered pretty much everything I thought about. If I missed anything, just tell me and I will edit the post.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What about you guys? What's your development environment?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2013/01/23/development-environment/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2013/01/23/development-environment/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>A little LESS puzzle</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi guys! What do you think of a little puzzle to wake up your neurons? I think I've found something tricky enough to worth a blog post and a little challenge about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First of all, this will be a LESS puzzle, so if you're really unfamiliar with this CSS preprocessor, I think you might feel a bit lost here. Sorry! :(&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;requirements&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What are the requirements&lt;a href=&quot;#requirements&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So the main idea is to enable a Google Web Font using a variable to have only one occurrence of the font name without leaving the stylesheet. Let me explain the requirements a little better:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick a Google font &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/webfonts&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click on &quot;Quick use&quot;, then &quot;@import&quot;, and copy the given URL to your clipboard,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open &lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io&quot;&gt;CodePen&lt;/a&gt;, click on &quot;New pen&quot; and pick LESS as a CSS preprocessor,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a variable for the font name, like this &lt;code&gt;@my-font: &quot;NameOfMyFont&quot;;&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Import the font from Google CDN with &lt;code&gt;@import url()&lt;/code&gt; using the variable as the font name in the URL,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give any element (&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; would be good) this font.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bonus:&lt;/strong&gt; make it work with compound font names (such as &quot;Roboto Condensed&quot;).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Accustomed to SASS like me will wonder where is the difficulty in this little exercise. Problem is LESS is extremely annoying when it comes to both url() and string concatenation. I partially covered the topic in &lt;a href=&quot;less-to-sass&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;/* SASS version */

$my-font: &quot;Merriweather&quot;;
$url: &quot;http://fonts.googleapis.com/css?family=#{$my-font}&quot;;
@import url($url);

h1 { font-family: $my-font; }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I struggled about one hour on this and couldn't make it work. All my respect to the one who will find the solution.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration:line-through&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/span&gt; Conclusion (edit January 26th, 2013)&lt;a href=&quot;#conclusion&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Loïc Giraudel (secondarily my dear brother) pointed out &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/cloudhead/less.js/issues/410&quot;&gt;a thread on GitHub&lt;/a&gt; mentioning that what I called a &quot;puzzle&quot; is in fact a real bug reported more than a year ago.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;However as of today, &lt;strong&gt;there is no fix for this neither is there a workaround&lt;/strong&gt;. So unless anyone comes up with a solution, this is currently not possible unfortunately.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Plus, the guys behind LESS imply fixing this bug would require a large amount of work and deep code restructuration.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;No luck.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 21 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2013/01/21/less-puzzle/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2013/01/21/less-puzzle/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>Blog changes</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi guys! It’s now been two months since I launched the new and active version of hugogiraudel.com and I took the opportunity to make a few changes. Let me introduce them, hoping you find them cool. :)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit&lt;/strong&gt; (January 22nd, 2013): I did a lot of changes after writing this post notably regarding SEO, performances and accessibility. Be sure &lt;a href=&quot;#features&quot;&gt;you read&lt;/a&gt; about it!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;layout&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Layout &lt;a href=&quot;#layout&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Content shuffling&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the layout has been updated! It’s now a 2-columns website. There are a number of reasons which made me change it but I think the most important one was that I was sick of seeing this stuff about me on the home page.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's be realistic: the main content is the blog not the 20 lines about me you could see everytime you loaded the first page. I wanted to enhance the articles so now the main page lists available articles. It seems muuuch better to me this way, what do you think?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;However, I wanted to provide visitors a quick glance at who I am, so I thought it could be a good idea to have a little sidebar to display informations about me. Now, I’m thinking of adding a picture of me in the sidebar; I know a lot of people do that on their blog. Any thought about that?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another thing that occured to me is that the lines were too long. It may be silly but when lines are too extented, it makes the reading more difficult. Now the main column is narrower, reading an article is easier and de facto nicer. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Responsive concern&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I felt like the old layout lacked of responsiveness. It wasn’t bad since it already provided a mobile-friendly version but I wanted a little bit more. This is why I landed on &lt;a href=&quot;http://cssgrid.net/&quot;&gt;the 1140px CSS grid&lt;/a&gt; by Andy Taylor.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m particularly happy with this grid system. It is very easy to set up and as you can see it’s pretty darn efficient!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Design &lt;a href=&quot;#design&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I didn’t change many things design speaking except the left border on the whole page to wedge everything from the left. I guess both the header and the footer are better delimited thanks to the solid borders; it’s probably better this way. Also, what do you think of the new Codrops tag on the home page? Pretty nice, right?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;However I slightly improved the mobile version, especially regarding the nav bar. It was a little bit messy with the previous version; it should now be properly centered. I'm thinking about centering the footer on mobiles as well. Don't know yet.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;development&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Development &lt;a href=&quot;#development&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I now rely on a PHP structure for convenience. Actually, I was kind of sick of having to edit a dozen of files every single time I want to make a tiny little change in the header or the footer. So I now have only PHP files, letting me use &lt;code&gt;include()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But, switching all my files to .php means a terrible thing: old URLs won’t work anymore! What about all these tweets, links and poor souls unable to reach my blog posts? No worry. My brother helped me doing some .htaccess in order to allow reaching the blog posts through old URLs. Big thanks to him. :)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;While we’re talking about .htaccess: you can now access articles without the file extension like this: &lt;a href=&quot;tools&quot;&gt;http://hugogiraudel/blog/tools&lt;/a&gt;. Pretty cool, right?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I also decided to rely on a CDN rather than on self hosting for &lt;a href=&quot;http://fortawesome.github.com/Font-Awesome/&quot;&gt;Font Awesome&lt;/a&gt; (now in v3.0.1 since a couple of days). I was especially concerned about the file size of my stylesheet because Font Awesome -as any other icon font- uses a lot of CSS. Anyway, I'm now using &lt;a href=&quot;http://timpietrusky.com&quot;&gt;Tim Pietrusky's&lt;/a&gt; CDN &lt;a href=&quot;http://weloveiconfonts.com&quot;&gt;WeLoveIconFonts&lt;/a&gt; and I'm pretty happy with it. ;)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;features&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Features&lt;a href=&quot;#features&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I tried to add a few features in order to make your experience nicer. Nothing big, just a few things which are -according to me- UX improvements. Among those:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Links to articles on the home page are now paginated in order to make the whole page lighter. Only the last 7 articles will be displayed (including Codrops ones) on the first page. To see older blog posts, you'll have to use the little buttons at the bottom of the screen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can now link to specific sections inside an article thanks to anchor tags on titles. When you hover a level-2 title (like &quot;Features&quot; or &quot;Performances&quot; for example), you'll see a little # character appearing. Click on it to have a section-specific URL.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;performances&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Performances&lt;a href=&quot;#Performances&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p class=&quot;pull-right&quot;&gt;I always try to make the page as fast as I can.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm kind of psychotic when it comes to performance. I always try to make the page as fast as I can. I'm really pissed off when I'm waiting for a page to load more than 2 seconds, so I tried to do my best to make the loading time as quick as possible.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Among the many things I did on the topic, I:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Did a lot of work on the CSS to clean it, make it faster, with less selectors, faster selectors, ans so on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reduced the number of HTTP requests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Am still working on the JavaScript part to make it asynchronous.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Asked &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/timpietrusky&quot;&gt;Tim Pietrusky&lt;/a&gt; to improve caching and compressing at &lt;a href=&quot;http://weloveiconfonts.com&quot;&gt;WeLoveIconFonts.com&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks dude!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;accessibility&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Accessibility&lt;a href=&quot;#accessibility&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know if it's a sudden realisation or the recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://a11yproject.com/&quot;&gt;A11y project&lt;/a&gt; which motivated me to do that but I took some time to improve accessibility on the site. Plus, it gave me the opportunity to learn some things on the topic.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First of all, I switched a bunch of my divs to &quot;new&quot; HTML5 elements. So I'm now using &amp;lt;header&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;article&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;aside&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;footer&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;section&amp;gt;, and so on. I must say it feels right, really.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I dug a little into ARIA roles. I have to say I didn't know it was such a deep and complex topic, so I may have understand a few things wrong. Anyway, I added a &lt;code&gt;role=&quot;&quot;&lt;/code&gt; attribute to many elements in the site, especially on the home page.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I also gave a few tries to keyboard navigations and I have to say it's really not that bad. If you have a few minutes left, try it on the home page and tell me what you think about it. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;By the way, if some accessibility ninja is passing by and finds something wrong, please be sure to tell me. :)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;seo&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;SEO&lt;a href=&quot;#seo&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Microdatas&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;SEO, big thing! I decided to push it one step further by trying microdatas. Man, this is not an easy thing. If you're not familiar with microdatas, the main idea is to label content to describe a specific type of information (person, event, review, etc.). This aims at helping search engine bots understanding  the content they index.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now if you inspect the sidebar code, you might see some microdatas about me including name, job title, nationality, urls, and so on. I believe it will help search engines indexing datas about me. We'll see if it works.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Hidden content&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I also edited the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/wesnolte/Pajinate&quot;&gt;jQuery plugin&lt;/a&gt; I use for pagination on the home page because it was using &lt;code&gt;.hide()&lt;/code&gt; to hide content from other pages but the current one. And you're not without knowing search engines don't index stuff set to &lt;code&gt;display: none;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I gathered my courage, opened the file and changed those hide and show methods by a class toggling. This class hides things with CSS, letting search engine index the content. It may sound silly but for a JS douche like me, editing a plugin is a pretty big deal. :D&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;to-do&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;To do &lt;a href=&quot;#to-do&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You tell me. If you have any request, comment, advise or any feedback to do, be sure to speak. Thanks a lot.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2013/01/17/blog-changes/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2013/01/17/blog-changes/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>Understanding the CSS clip property</title>
				<description>
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2013/01/16/codrops-css-clip/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2013/01/16/codrops-css-clip/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>Handy tools I use for front-end development</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’ve been thinking (yeah, true story). And it occured to me, it would be a good idea to write a little blog post about some of the cool tools I use almost everyday. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you're a webdesigner or developer, you’ve probably already stumbled upon some wonderful online tools / services. Not necessarly complicated things, just things you definitely need. There are really a bunch of them, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://wildwebwatch.com&quot;&gt;Wild Web Watch&lt;/a&gt; is pretty much focused on listing them, but I’d like to focus on just a few of them. The ones I use very often.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So here are the tools I’ll cover in this article:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#css-coloratum&quot;&gt;CSS Coloratum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#weloveiconfonts&quot;&gt;WeLoveIconFonts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#pagespeedinsights&quot;&gt;PageSpeed Insights&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#colorzilla&quot;&gt;Colorzilla Extension&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#colorzilla&quot;&gt;Colorzilla Gradient Generator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#caniuse&quot;&gt;CanIUse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;css-coloratum&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;CSS Coloratum&lt;a href=&quot;#css-coloratum&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Author: Lea Verou&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Link: &lt;a href=&quot;http://css.coloratum.com/&quot;&gt;http://css.coloratum.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Category: Design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;CSS Coloratum is a handful tool helping you convert colors in different syntaxes. It currently supports keywords, hexadecimal, RGB and HSL. Plus, it shows a preview.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Probably one of the best tools I know, especially when you’re working with hexadecimal colors you want to convert to colors accepting an alpha value (RGBa / HSLa).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tools__css-coloratum.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;CSS Coloratum&quot;&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;weloveiconfonts&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;WeLoveIconFonts&lt;a href=&quot;#weloveiconfonts&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Author: Tim Pietrusky&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Link: &lt;a href=&quot;http://weloveiconfonts.com&quot;&gt;http://weloveiconfonts.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Category: Development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;WeLoveIconFonts (yes we do!) is some kind of CDN (Content Delivery Network) for icon fonts, like Google Web Fonts for web fonts. It currently supports Brandico, Entypo, Font Awesome, Fontelico, Maki, OpenWeb Icons, Typicons and Zocial.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s very easy to use. You pick one or more fonts, you copy the @import line into your stylesheet and you’re done. You can put icons all over your website. No more struggle with font files.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tools__weloveiconfonts.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;WeLoveIconFonts&quot;&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;pagespeedinsights&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;PageSpeed Insights&lt;a href=&quot;#pagespeedinsights&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Author: Google&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Link: &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/speed/pagespeed/insights&quot;&gt;https://developers.google...&lt;/a&gt; (+ &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/pagespeed-insights-by-goo/gplegfbjlmmehdoakndmohflojccocli?utm_source=chrome-ntp-icon&quot;&gt;Chrome&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/speed/docs/insights/using_firefox&quot;&gt;Firefox&lt;/a&gt; extensions&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Category: Optimization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;PageSpeed Insights is a tool made by Google which analyzes the content of a web page, then generates suggestions to make things faster. What I really like about PSI is it also exists as a Chrome and a Firefox extension, which means you can inspect your page directly from the WebDeveloper Tools / Firebug. Isn’t that awesome?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tools__page-speed-insights.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;PageSpeed Insights&quot;&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;colorzilla&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Colorzilla&lt;a href=&quot;#colorzilla&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Author: Colorzilla&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Link: &lt;a href=&quot;http://colorzilla.com/&quot;&gt;http://colorzilla.com/&lt;/a&gt; (+ &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.colorzilla.com/chrome/&quot;&gt;Chrome&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.colorzilla.com/firefox/&quot;&gt;Firefox&lt;/a&gt; extensions)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Category: Design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;ColorZilla provides 2 really awesome things: a CSS gradient generator and a Chrome / Firefox extension to deal with colors. I really recommand the 2, so I’ll talk about both.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Colorzilla Gradient Generator&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Colorzilla Gradient Generator is, well, a CSS gradient generator and probably the best you’ll find so far. It provides a bunch of options like gradient orientation, reversing, size, IE support with filters, color adjustments and much more. And of course, you can copy and paste the CSS code for all browsers. Plus, it also provides 137 presets gradients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tools__cz-gradient-generator.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ColorZilla Gradient Generator&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Colorzilla Extension&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tools__cz-extension.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ColorZilla extension&quot; class=&quot;pull-image--right&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Colorzilla is also a Chrome / Firefox extension to manage colors. This extension provides a lot of features, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An eyedropper (with copy to clipboard feature)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An advanced color picker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A webpage color analyzer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A palette viewer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A color history&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keyboard shortcuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know there are a bunch of colorpickers / eyedropper extensions outhere but you want find any like this. Colorzilla is really, really awesome and I wonder how I could work so long without using it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;caniuse&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;CanIUse&lt;a href=&quot;#caniuse&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Author: Alexis Deveria&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Link: &lt;a href=&quot;http://weloveiconfont.com&quot;&gt;http://caniuse.com/&lt;/a&gt; (+ &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/can-i-use/kinefpelfmogilfkmjlbfkamgmofmedf/reviews?utm_source=chrome-ntp-icon&quot;&gt;Chrome extension&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Category: Development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CanIUse.com is the perfect tool when building HTML5 and CSS3 websites or applications. It groups together compatibility tables for most of HTML5, CSS3, SVG and JS API features. From there, you have access to browser support statistics coming from StatCounters for both desktop and mobiles browsers plus some various notes you may want to know about before using a feature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This awesome tool has quickly become &lt;strong&gt;the reference&lt;/strong&gt; when it comes to browser support documentation. I use it almost everyday and I would probably be lost without it. As a front-developer, it's a really really useful tool. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also exists as a Chrome extension meaning you can search for features directly into your browser without having to visit caniuse.com but I don't use it much since the search engine isn't that good (&quot;border-image&quot; doesn't give any result while &quot;border image&quot; does for example).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tools__caniuse.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Can I Use&quot;&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;final-words&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Final words&lt;a href=&quot;#final-words&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are plenty more tools I'd like to talk about but I think it will be for another article. Enough for one day! What about you guys, what are the tools you always use? Be sure to share your opinion!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2013/01/14/tools/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2013/01/14/tools/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>How I built a Tetris with C# and Unity</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of my formation in programming sciences, I had the opportunity to build a little Tetris game with C# on Unity and I thought it could be a good idea to write a little blog post about my experience. Plus, it changes a little from CSS things.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why Tetris?&lt;/strong&gt; Well first, it's a pretty classic game which doesn't need a good design layer to be fun to play. Plus, the logic behind the game is simple enough to start, but there are still some difficulties which are very interesting to learn from.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a reminder:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unity_(game_engine)&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Unity is a cross-platform game engine and IDE developed by Unity Technologies, targeting web plugins, desktop platforms and mobile devices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C_Sharp_(programming_language)&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C#&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: C# is a programming language developed by Microsoft within its .NET initiative and later approved as a standard by ECMA and ISO.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you don't give a fuck about how I built this up and simply want to give it a try, please refer to &lt;a href=&quot;#play&quot;&gt;this section&lt;/a&gt; at the bottom of the article. Have fun! ;)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer!&lt;/strong&gt; Please, understand this game is one of my first works in Unity with C#, so it’s pretty dirty. There are still some bugs, and there have been absolutely no work on the design layer. &lt;strong&gt;The point was to try to make a game which is playable&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s more than enough for a first work, don’t you think?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;making-of&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The making of &lt;a href=&quot;#making-of&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tetris__tetris.jpg&quot; class=&quot;pull-image--right&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Neuron Tetris&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Before doing any code, I had the &quot;how the fuck am I supposed to do this?&quot; moment. I had to think about the process behind the program, the way it would work. This is what I started with:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instantiate a random brick&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allow move and rotate on the current brick&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stop the brick when its bottom hits another brick or the floor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Destroy complete lines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Goto(1);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even if I’m clearly not a good C# developer neither I'm a Unity ninja, I was pretty confident with the making of this game. Given the process above, I thought it would be fairly easy to do. Boy, I was wrong. It’s been rough. Let’s see why!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;When things go wrong&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Collision detection&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are a few things that were really not easy to do with my current skills and knowledge of both the language and the program but one was really above all: &lt;strong&gt;collision detection&lt;/strong&gt;. What a bitch.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Basically, I wanted to:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;prevent the brick from crossing left and right edges of the frame&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;prevent the brick from crossing another brick&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;stop the brick when hitting either the floor or another brick&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At a first glance, it seems easy, especially when you know Unity engine implements a collision detection system. To put it simple, the collision detection module from Unity permanently checks if something is touching your current item. If there is, it returns the item touching it, else it returns false.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First problem: how to distinguish bottom collisions from side collisions? Because this isn’t the same thing. If you detect a collision on the bottom, you have to make the brick stop moving, and if you detect a collision on a side, you have to prevent the user to move the brick on this side.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve spend hours trying to make it work with no success, so I ended using a completely different approach: &lt;strong&gt;rays&lt;/strong&gt;. To put it simple, you can cast an invisible ray from the center of an item in the direction you want and to the distance you want. From there, it returns you a boolean: there is something or there is not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So what I did was casting rays in 3 direction (left, bottom, right) at a very short distance. If the ray returns something on a side, I prevent the brick from moving on this side. If there is something below, I stop the brick and instantiate a new one. It seems to work well.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Brick positioning&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another problem of mine was placing the bricks correctly. During the first phase of testing, bricks were slightly overlapping each other (see figure). Not much, but enough to be seen and to involve some line destroying issues.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tetris__bricks-overlapping.png&quot; class=&quot;img-right mt05 bordered&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was caused by the collision detection problem. Because whatever the method I could use (rays, OnCollisionEnter, OnTriggerEnter, …), the brick wasn’t stopped at the right position. It was always “more or less&quot; where it should have ended. This lack of accuracy was problematic.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I ended doing something I didn’t want to, but I had no choice: brick repositioning after landing. Basically, it means when a brick stops moving, I round up its coordinates to place it where it should have ended. It’s not great, it involves some calculations, but I couldn’t think of any other option to fix this issue.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Brick rotation&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I started coding, I was expecting the brick rotation to be very simple. In some way, I wasn't wrong: make the brick rotate on itself is the easy part. When pressing top or bottom arrow, the brick makes a 90° rotation clockwise or counter-clockwise, no problem.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tetris__tetris-bug.png&quot; class=&quot;pull-image--right&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was much harder however was &lt;strong&gt;prevent the rotation when too close to the wall&lt;/strong&gt;. Rotating a red bar near the wall could mean wedging the bar into the wall. I succeded in preventing the rotation when too close to the wall, however there is still a bug with the purple L brick which cannot rotate when placed at a 1-unit gap from the wall. Sadly, I don't know how to fix it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The other big problem I had and still have with brick rotation is rotating near another brick. Unlike the walls, there is no restriction for rotating a brick near another one, meaning you can overlap bricks with this method. In most cases, this bug won't be noticed because the common behaviour when playing Tetris is rotating and moving the brick while falling, not moving the brick at the very last moment of its fall. Still, there is a bug I couldn't fix.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;improvements&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Let's make improvements &lt;a href=&quot;#improvements&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Once I figured out how to fix most of the previously seen problems, it was time to do some improvements to make the game enjoyable. This includes increasing difficulty overtime, displaying the next brick, showing the score, having a main screen, allow pause, and so on. Actually,  it's kind of all the features. Making the game work is the hard part, but making the game cool is very important as well.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tetris__tetris-options.jpg&quot; class=&quot;pull-image--right&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Score&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Showing the score was very easy to do. Basically, everytime a brick is spawned a score variable is incremented by 10 points. When a line is destroyed, the score variable gains 100 points. What was a little harder was displaying the score on the main screen once you lose the game. (This makes me notice I forgot to reset the number of lines when playing again. :x)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On Unity, when you want to do various &quot;levels&quot;, you have to create multiple scenes. Like you would do in Flash if you know what I mean. So in our case, the main menu is a scene, and the game is another one. Problem is, objects in a scene are not accessible from another scene by default, so I had to do some trickery.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Difficulty&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To increase the difficulty over time, I had multiple options:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Classic Tetris way: you have to do X lines to change level. Each level is faster than the previous one. However, it would have required me to do multiple scenes which would have pissed me off, so it was not an option to me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increase speed over time since game start: it didn't seem very accurate to me since; the difficulty has to go higher when you can stand it, not when you're struggling to place your bricks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increase speed over score: something like &lt;code&gt;speed = score / 100&lt;/code&gt; or I don't know. Same reason as above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increase speed over completed lines: every time a line is completed, the speed increases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I decided to increase speed every time you complete a line. Not much, so you don't notice it, but progressively, you're starting to feel it. This option seems great to me because it increases speed only when you're winning without requiring any other scene breaking the game flow.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From there, displaying some kind of level was only a math concern. The result is you're passing a level every 10 lines. I think it's pretty accurate regarding the Classic Tetris.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Rotating camera&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An interesting point of making a game on Unity is you're using 3D. You can choose to ignore it, but I feel like it can be a plus to the game when used correctly (which is not the case in this game :D). I wanted to try slowly moving the camera during the game to increase difficulty. Hopefully, I didn't have to struggle with quaternion calculations for rotation concerns since I managed to do everything directly in the IDE with default animations.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tetris__tetris-camera.jpg&quot; class=&quot;pull-image--right&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was pretty easy to do, however I felt like it could be really annoying for some people (including me) to have the camera moving permanently so I simply added an option to enable/disable it. The &lt;code&gt;C&lt;/code&gt; key in game, as in camera. True story.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;play&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;About the game&lt;a href=&quot;#play&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer (once again)!&lt;/strong&gt; This game is kind of a learning experiment so it may be pretty dirty. As explained above, there are still some bugs and the design layer hasn't been done at all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Features&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Classic tetris gameplay&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3D view&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Score + number of lines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kind of levels with speed increase&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quick fall while pressing space&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preview of next brick&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pause&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rotating camera&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Epic 8-bit Tetris soundtrack&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Play it!&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even if it’s not perfect, I still have fun playing it, you can try it if you want:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;http://tank-a-faire.com/tetris/WebPlayer.html&quot;&gt;Play online&lt;/a&gt;; you’ll be ask to download Unity’s Web Player, hopefully it’s extremely light and quick to install&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try the &lt;a href=&quot;http://tank-a-faire.com/tetris/flash/tetris.html&quot;&gt;Flash version&lt;/a&gt; (a bit laggy) if you don't want to download the UWP&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;http://tank-a-faire.com/tetris/windows/tetris.zip&quot;&gt;Download it for Windows 64 bits&lt;/a&gt; (~8Mb)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;http://tank-a-faire.com/tetris/mac/tetris.app.zip&quot;&gt;Download it for Mac OS&lt;/a&gt; (~8Mb)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;to-do&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What's next?&lt;a href=&quot;#to-do&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't know yet if I'm going to continue this game, but I think it's a good start, so I may try to improve it in a not so far future. I have a few plans to make it nicer, including:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fixing the brick rotation bugs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fixing the number of lines bug&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improving the design layer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hiding the game when paused&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Giving the ability to disable music&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improving performances&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making it run on mobile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So guys, how far did you manage to go? My best score is 9840 points, level 7 I guess.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script&gt;var disqus_url = &quot;http://hugogiraudel.com/blog/tetris&quot;;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 20 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/12/20/tetris/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/12/20/tetris/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>CSS Clicks event</title>
				<description>
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 17 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/12/17/codrops-css-click-events/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/12/17/codrops-css-click-events/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>How I start a new project</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi guys! I recently asked on Twitter a topic to blog about because I had frankly no idea. Christoph Rumpel (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/christophrumpel&quot;&gt;@christophrumpel&lt;/a&gt;) proposed something about the way I start a new project. I thought it could be a good idea, plus I’m currently working on a new project at work so it may help me as well!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ll probably talk a lot about my blog in this article because it’s the latest project I ran, and I really tried to make things right. So I may do some parallelisms as examples. Anyway, let's go!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;thinking&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The thinking&lt;a href=&quot;#thinking&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The very first thing I do when starting a new web project is &lt;strong&gt;thinking&lt;/strong&gt;. I spend like days boggling my mind about the way I should do this and this, and this... Jumping on the IDE to start coding isn’t a good idea. I used to do this in the past, and it often results in costly mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, let’s think about it. And when I think I have a decent idea of what it’s going to look like, I’m sketching some sort of schedule. In most cases, this is as follow:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write the objectives&lt;/strong&gt;. Who’s the target? What’s the point? What are the main features?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Find the content&lt;/strong&gt;. What do I have? What is my content, what will fit the blank pages?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Think about the arborescence&lt;/strong&gt;, the structure of the site / application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make a sketch&lt;/strong&gt;, then a mockup. I start large then I go to the details.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Develop&lt;/strong&gt;. Yaaay, let’s run the IDE and write some lines of code!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Things may vary depending on what’s the project, what’s its scale and such but in most cases this is the process I try to follow. I think it’s very important to make things in the right order; &lt;strong&gt;the objectives define the content which defines the architecture, which defines the design, which defines the way to code&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Please note this only my way of doing, do not take this as the Holy Bible. And please be sure to tell if you feel like something is wrong here. Okay so now we have some kind of way to go, let’s dig in each part a little deepier, shall we?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;objectives&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The objectives&lt;a href=&quot;#objectives&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is the very first thing you have to do. Actually, it should even be implicit since you need a goal in order to achieve something. When you eat, it’s because you’re hungry. When you open a new tab on your browser, it’s because you want to make a search or visit a website. If you want to make a website or an application, it’s to suit some needs, to fill a goal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I redesigned my website because the old one was just a single page with 5 lines of text on it, I tried to think about what would this site be for. Here is what I came with:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a landing page for people looking for me for any reason&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put my resume online&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Talk about things on what we can call a blog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even if it’s implicit, it’s important to write things down. I often found myself in the past coding something I hadn’t think about at first, which resulted in refactoring large chunks of code. Writing things down from the beginning is a good way to know where you’re going.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;content&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The content&lt;a href=&quot;#content&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now we have thought about the goal of the site/application, it’s time to &lt;strong&gt;think about the content&lt;/strong&gt; which will fill that goal. &lt;strong&gt;There can be no site without content&lt;/strong&gt;, it’s lame and completely useless. Sometimes I see people asking for a website without anything to put in and I wonder what is the point? Having a place on the internet with your name on it? Okay actually that’s kind of cool, but that’s even better if you have things to tell.&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My way to do is to find the maximum of content for each of the objectives of the site/application. Then, if there is too much, I filter to keep only the best ideas. Too much is better than too few. You might want to readnotes from Luke Wroblewski about Jeffrey Zeldman talk at AEA Washington DC about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lukew.com/ff/entry.asp?1598&quot;&gt;&quot;Content first&quot;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this website, the content was pretty straight forward: the landing page should have some informations about me (like contact stuff) and about &lt;a href=&quot;http://wildwebwatch.com&quot;&gt;Wild Web Watch&lt;/a&gt;, one of my main projects. The resume should be, well, my resume. And I had already 2 ideas of articles for the new blog (&lt;a href=&quot;redesign-blog.html&quot;&gt;one about the redesign&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;less-to-sass.html&quot;&gt;one about CSS preprocessors&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;arborescence&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The arborescence&lt;a href=&quot;#arborescence&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we managed to find some general content for our website/application. We can now think about the architecture of the whole thing. How will it be divided? In most cases, this step is pretty easy to do. You can think of it as “what my main navigation will look like?”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Maybe it’ll have a contact page, a products page, a shop section and so on. Then, ask yourself if there will be another level of structure in a section. Shop may contain various other sections. All of this will give you a structure for your site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This site's structure is very easy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Home&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blog
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Articles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Resume&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plus, it occured to me doing that helps me creating the development environment during when I come to the coding part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The design&lt;a href=&quot;#design&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is when things are getting fun. Yeah cause the previous steps were pretty boring, right? Who want to spend hours thinking about something? WE WANT TO MAKE THINGS! So here it is. From now on, it’s like doing a bunch of stuff. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there is still no code. We first have to &lt;strong&gt;draw a sketch&lt;/strong&gt; of the website/application. What will it look like? Physically I mean. This is where I’m facing some troubles as far as I am concerned. If like me you never know how to start, then I figured out asking some very basic questions often help finding out where to start. Things like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What layout do I want (number of columns, structure, etc.)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What will be the &lt;a href=&quot;http://tympanus.net/codrops/2012/09/17/build-a-color-scheme-the-fundamentals/&quot; title=&quot;Build a color scheme: the fundamentals&quot;&gt;color scheme&lt;/a&gt; and how many colors will compose it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do I want to put &lt;a href=&quot;http://css-tricks.com/responsive-web-above-the-fold/&quot; title=&quot;Responsive Web Design - Above the fold&quot;&gt;above the fold&lt;/a&gt; (main content, important stuff)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I like starting on paper&lt;/strong&gt;. I think it’s easier because you can’t hide behind visual effects like gradients, shadows and such. It’s all about structure and where will be positioned the various elements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I’m finally happy with a sketch, I try to redo it on my computer. Sometimes I go straight to CSS when things look quite simple, but it occured to me there are better ways to go. I think one of the best would be to use an online tool like &lt;a href=&quot;http://wireframe.cc/&quot;&gt;WireFrame.cc&lt;/a&gt; (or &lt;a href=&quot;http://styloapp.com&quot;&gt;StyloApp&lt;/a&gt;) to make a nicer sketch than the one you drew on paper but still focused on structure, not visual effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wcc.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;WireFrame.cc&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it looks good, I personally go for CSS. Some people prefer working a detailed mockup on PhotoShop first but since I’m shitty as hell when it comes to this software and I’m quite confident with CSS, I prefer go straight with CSS and design in the browser. Plus, designing in the browser is very trend those days!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I know some designers simply can not design in the browser because they turn their brain to &quot;technical mode&quot;, losing their creative mind. I don't blame at all since I'm not a designer, browser or not browser. Anyway, if you plan on using Photoshop, I’d suggest not doing too much on visual effects but it’s more like a matter of opinion here. I think this stuff can be figured out afterwards, and not necessarly during the design process but I could be wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;development&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The development&lt;a href=&quot;#development&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yaaaaay! Here comes the code! The funny part. But before coding, I like to set up my workflow in order to make everything right for the whole development process. Setting up the working environment can mean a lot of things depending on the project:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Building the arborescence (creating folders and such)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setting up the development environment (EasyPHP/Mamp, JDK, Sass &amp;amp; Compass, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creating some default files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whatever you think is good&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the way I go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Creating the project&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really like when things are well ordered plus I don’t want to keep messing with relative paths, so I like to make the whole arborescence at first to not bother about it anymore. Here is the way I do it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;sass/&lt;/code&gt; for SCSS stylesheets if I use Sass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;stylesheets/&lt;/code&gt; for CSS stylesheets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;scripts/&lt;/code&gt; for JavaScript scripts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;images/&lt;/code&gt; for images&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;fonts/&lt;/code&gt; for both web and icon fonts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;feeds/&lt;/code&gt; for RSS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;resources/&lt;/code&gt; for various stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This site also uses a &lt;code&gt;blog/&lt;/code&gt; folder and a &lt;code&gt;resume/&lt;/code&gt; folder to keep things clean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A project involving some kind of back-office would also include a fake &lt;code&gt;admin/&lt;/code&gt; folder (with a fake login form) and a real admin folder with some random name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Setting up the development environment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on the project, the development environment may vary. A PHP project requires EasyPHP or Mamp to work, a Java-based project would require JDK, and so on. Even for the front-end side, you may want to have some tools like pre-processors (Markdown for HTML, Sass for CSS, CoffeeScript for JS or whatever).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of preprocessors, I build most of my projects on Sass so there are a few things I do before coding. I don’t know about you, but I don’t use any tool to manage Sass stuff (like Compass.app or CodeKit). Not because I'm a command-line nerd but because I work on different computers with different OS, meaning I would have to install everything all over again. So I tend to do Sass stuff with command lines through Ruby Command Prompt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on what I need for the project, I might also need some scripts like jQuery, Modernizr, Prefixfree, Prism or other things. I may also want to include an icon font I don't know, so I download files before going any further, just in case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Creating default files&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To speed up the development time, I like to do all the dirty stuff at the beginning of a project to be able to focus on the cool stuff without being interrupted. So I often create a bunch of files I know I will have to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;HTML&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following code is a valid HTML document which can be used to create any page in the site. Its content may vary according to the needs of the project but in most cases it includes conditional HTML classes, IE stylesheet, commented scripts, jQuery call, Google Analytics snippet and so on. Everything's ready!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-markup&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!DOCTYPE html&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;html class=&quot;no-js&quot;&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;head&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;lt;meta charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&amp;amp;gt;
&amp;amp;lt;meta http-equiv=&quot;X-UA-Compatible&quot; content=&quot;IE=edge,chrome=1&quot;&amp;amp;gt;
&amp;amp;lt;meta name=&quot;viewport&quot; content=&quot;width=device-width&quot;&amp;amp;gt;
&amp;amp;lt;title&amp;amp;gt;New title&amp;amp;lt;/title&amp;amp;gt;
&amp;amp;lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; type=&quot;text/css&quot; href=&quot;stylesheets/styles.min.css&quot;&amp;amp;gt;
&amp;amp;lt;!--[if lte IE 7]&amp;amp;gt; &amp;amp;lt;link rel=&quot;stylesheet&quot; type=&quot;text/css&quot; href=&quot;stylesheets/ie.css&quot;&amp;amp;gt; &amp;amp;lt;![endif]--&amp;amp;gt;
&amp;amp;lt;!--[if lt IE 9]&amp;amp;gt; &amp;amp;lt;script src=&quot;http://html5shiv.googlecode.com/svn/trunk/html5.js&quot;&amp;amp;gt;&amp;amp;lt;/script&amp;amp;gt; &amp;amp;lt;![endif]--&amp;amp;gt;
&amp;amp;lt;!-- &amp;amp;lt;script src=&quot;scripts/modernizr-2.6.2.min.js&quot;&amp;amp;gt;&amp;amp;lt;/script&amp;gt; --&amp;amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;lt;script src=&quot;//ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/1.8.2/jquery.min.js&quot;&amp;amp;gt;&amp;amp;lt;/script&amp;amp;gt;
&amp;amp;lt;script&amp;amp;gt;window.jQuery || document.write('&amp;amp;lt;script src=&quot;js/jquery-1.8.2.min.js&quot;&amp;amp;gt;&amp;amp;lt;\/script&amp;amp;gt;')&amp;amp;lt;/script&amp;amp;gt;      

&amp;amp;lt;!-- &amp;amp;lt;script src=&quot;js/functions.js&quot;&amp;amp;gt;&amp;amp;lt;/script&amp;amp;gt; --&amp;amp;gt;
&amp;amp;lt;!-- &amp;amp;lt;script&amp;amp;gt;
var _gaq=[['_setAccount','UA-XXXXX-X'],['_trackPageview']];
(function(d,t){var g=d.createElement(t),s=d.getElementsByTagName(t)[0];
g.src=('https:'==location.protocol?'//ssl':'//www')+'.google-analytics.com/ga.js';
s.parentNode.insertBefore(g,s)}(document,'script'));
&amp;amp;lt;/script&amp;amp;gt; --&amp;amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Stylesheets&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s cool with Sass it’s it gives you the option to use a bunch of stylesheets and concatenate all of them into one single file without any performance loss. The following is my &lt;code&gt;styles.scss&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;@import “mixins”;
@import &quot;variables&quot;;
@import &quot;default&quot;;
@import &quot;reset&quot;;
@import &quot;typography&quot;;
@import &quot;grid&quot;;
@import &quot;font-awesome&quot;;
@import &quot;main&quot;;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When compiled, it takes all the following SCSS stylesheets and concatenate and compress all of them into one single &lt;code&gt;styles.min.css&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;em&gt;variables.scss&lt;/code&gt; contains things like colors, default margins and such&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;/em&gt;default.scss&lt;/code&gt; has stuff like border-box, clearfix and useful classes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;em&gt;reset.scss&lt;/code&gt; contains Eric Meyer’s CSS reset&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;/em&gt;typography.scss&lt;/code&gt; comes from Twitter Bootstrap and includes a bunch of typographic rules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;em&gt;grid.scss&lt;/code&gt; is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cssgrid.net/&quot;&gt;1140px Grid&lt;/a&gt; stylesheet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;/em&gt;font-awesome.scss&lt;/code&gt; is the FA stylesheet, now replaced by the CDN from Tim Pietrusky &lt;a href=&quot;http://weloveiconfonts.com&quot;&gt;WeLoveIconFonts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;_main.scss&lt;/code&gt; contains stuff relative to the current project, the actual CSS (empty at first)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;JavaScript&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most projects require at least a little bit of JavaScript. Especially since I'm really not good at JavaScript, meaning I feel like I have to use jQuery in order to achieve anything. Anyway, I use to have a few things in the scripts/ folder to begin with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The last and minified version of jQuery in case Google's CDN is unavailable (currently &lt;code&gt;jquery-1.8.2.min.js&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The last and minified version of Modernizr to do some feature detection for graceful degradation (currently &lt;code&gt;modernizr-2.6.2.min.js&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;functions.js&lt;/code&gt; where I put my stuff to run various things&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past, I used to use Prefix-free as well for CSS prefixing but I don't anymore since Compass does it for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, once I've done all this stuff, I can go further into the actual development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;final-words&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Final words&lt;a href=&quot;#final-words&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess I've covered pretty much everything I'm dealing with when starting a new project. Some things may vary depending on the project, but here is the general process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about you? How do you deal with another project? What's your workflow?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/12/12/process/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/12/12/process/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>Colors in CSS</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi everyone! Today, we will talk about colors in CSS. There are many color specifications and we'll be talking about their history, what they mean and how to use them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you'd like to read about how to build a color scheme for a website then you might be interested in this article &lt;a href=&quot;http://tympanus.net/codrops/2012/09/17/build-a-color-scheme-the-fundamentals/&quot;&gt;Build a color scheme: the fundamentals&lt;/a&gt;, or the article &lt;a href=&quot;http://tympanus.net/codrops/2012/02/28/principles-of-color-and-the-color-wheel/&quot; title=&quot;Principles of Color and the Color Wheel&quot;&gt;Principles of Color and the Color Wheel&lt;/a&gt; if you'd like to read about the color wheel.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We will see how we can define colors in style sheets, what each one can be used for and more. But first, let me introduce the topic.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Various types of colors in CSS&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Colors in CSS are defined on a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SRGB&quot;&gt;sRGB&lt;/a&gt; color space. sRGB stands for &quot;Standard Red Green Blue&quot; where colors are defined through three channels: Red, Green and Blue.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From there, we have various ways to describe color with CSS. Some of them like keywords and hexadecimal has been there almost since the beginning of the web, while other like HSL or RGB came later.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#rgb&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RGB&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;RGBA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#hex&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hexadecimal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#keywords&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keywords&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (+transparent and currentColor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#hsl&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HSL&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;HSLA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#system-colors&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;System colors&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's talk about each one of these definitions to understand them better.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;rgb&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;RGB&lt;a href=&quot;#rgb&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let me start with the RGB syntax since it’s the most fundamental thing to understand in order to comprehend how other notations like hexadecimal work. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What is RGB?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As I said above, RGB stands for Red, Green and Blue. Remember when you were a little kid and were painting with some cheap watercolor? Well, this is kind of the same thing, except that colors behave a little bit differently on screen and on paper. Let me explain myself:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;On paper&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;On screen&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Main colors are Red, Yellow and Blue&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Main colors are Red, Green and Blue&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Mixing 3 colors makes a brownish black&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Mixing 3 colors makes a grey shade&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A bit of blue + some red make nice purple&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A bit of blue + some red make dark purple&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The less color you use, the brighter it is&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The less color you use, the darker it is&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Representation is a circle with neither white nor black&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Representation is a cube with black and white&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/css-colors__color-cube.jpg&quot; class=&quot;pull-image--left&quot; alt=&quot;Color Cube&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;bq1&quot;&gt;This picture is the RGB color model mapped to a cube. What you can see is this: the horizontal x-axis as red values increasing to the left, y-axis as blue increasing to the lower right, and the vertical z-axis as green towards the top. The origin, black, is the vertex hidden from the view.&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;h3 style=&quot;clear:both&quot;&gt;How do we define RGB colors?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To describe a color using the RGB model, you have to define a value for the red channel, a value for the green channel and a value for the blue channel. Okay, but what type of value? Percentages? Arbitrary? Any?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A RGB value can be defined using four different syntaxes but only two of them are available in CSS:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A percentage from 0% (black) to 100% (white)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An integer value from 0 (black) to 255 (white); 255 is the range of a 8-bit byte&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A float number from 0 to 1 (0.58935); it’s more like a theoretical approach &lt;strong&gt;unavailable in CSS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A large integer 10, 16, 24, 32, 48 or even 64-bit units, but clearly that's &lt;strong&gt;unavailable in CSS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, summarized, we end up with two different ways to display CSS colors with the &lt;code&gt;rgb()&lt;/code&gt; function: percentages and integers between 0 and 255. Let’s illustrate this with an example, shall we?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;.black { /* I’m black! */
    color: rgb(0, 0, 0);
    color: rgb(0%, 0%, 0%);
}

.white { /* I’m white! */
    color: rgb(255, 255, 255);
    color: rgb(100%, 100%, 100%);
}

.purple { /* I’m medium purple! */
    color: rgb(128, 0, 128);
    color: rgb(50%, 0%, 50%);
}

.light-purple { /* I’m fuchsia! */
    color: rgb(255, 0, 255);
    color: rgb(100%, 0%, 100%);
}

.dark-purple { /* I’m deep purple! */
    color: rgb(64, 0, 64);
    color: rgb(25%, 0%, 25%);
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Important&lt;/strong&gt;: when using percentages, you have to set the unit even if it is 0. If you don’t, some browsers may be unable to parse it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;Note: even if the percentage version seems more intuitive, it’s actually the integer version that seems to be more commonly used.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What about the alpha-channel?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As seen previously, while using the RGB system we can also use an alpha channel which is by default set to 1. This channel allows us to modify the opacity of a color, or its transparency if you will.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To use this channel in CSS, you’ll call the &lt;code&gt;rgba()&lt;/code&gt; function instead of the &lt;code&gt;rgb()&lt;/code&gt;. However note the alpha-channel is always defined with a float clamped between 0 and 1.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;.black { /* I’m half transparent black! */
    color: rgba(0, 0, 0, 0.5);
    color: rgba(0%, 0%, 0%, 0.5);
}

.white { /* I’m 2/3 transparent white! */
    color: rgba(255, 255, 255, 0.33);
    color: rgba(100%, 100%, 100%, 0.33);
}

.red { /* I’m fully transparent red, so kind of invisible */
    color: rgba(255, 0, 0, 0);
    color: rgba(100%, 0%, 0%, 0);
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This can be very useful in various situation. Let’s say you have some kind of background image and want to write on it without losing readability or putting a big white box on top of it. This is the perfect usecase for RGBa!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;.parent {
    background-image: url(‘my-picture.jpg’);
}

.child {
    background: rgba(255, 255, 255, 0.75);
    color: rgb(51, 51, 51);
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This way, the child element will have a white background with 75% opacity, showing its parent’s background without risking any issue with readability.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;Note: when dealing with decimal values between 0 and 1, you don’t have to write the 0 before the dot. So you can write &lt;code&gt;rgba(0, 0, 0, .5)&lt;/code&gt; and still be perfectly valid.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: the &lt;code&gt;rgb()&lt;/code&gt; function is perfectly valid CSS2.1. However the &lt;code&gt;rgba()&lt;/code&gt; function is part of the CSS3 specification and is not supported by all browsers (Internet Explorer 6, 7, 8).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;hex&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Hexadecimal&lt;a href=&quot;#hex&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What is hexadecimal?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Most of the time, CSS colors are specified using the hexadecimal format which is a 6 (or 3) characters long string using numbers from 0 to 9 and letters from A to F, starting by the hash sign # (ex: #1A2B3C). We refer as this syntax as a “hex triplet”.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Okay, but what does this mean? I agree it’s not that simple. Basically, hexadecimal colors are some sort of code for RGB colors: the first two characters stand for the red value; the 3rd and 4th characters stand for greens; and the last two characters are here for the blue.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Since the range of a 8-bit byte is 256, we usually use a base 16 system to display values. This system is called hexadecimal. So basically those 3*2 digits stand for 3 values from 0 to 255 converted to base 16, as you would do in RGB.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Okay, I can understand you’re lost here, so we’ll try a little example. Let’s say you want to make a pure red (rgb(255, 0, 0)): thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;http://wims.unice.fr/wims/wims.cgi&quot;&gt;this awesome converter&lt;/a&gt;, you convert 255 to base 16 and know it equals FF. If you try to convert 0, you’ll see it’s 0 as well in base 16. So your hex triplet would be #FF0000. Simple, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So this was the theory, alright? It doesn’t mean you have to use a base 16 converter every single time you want to use a color in CSS. I’m simply explaining you how are hexadecimal colors composed. Now in real life, you’ll simply use a color palette like Photoshop or whatever.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;Note: you may see some hex triplets reduced to 3 digits instead of 6. It only happens when the two digits of each of the 3 components of the triplet are the same. To apply it on our previous example, the red color (#FF0000) can be written like #F00. If any of the 3 components have 2 different digits, you can’t do this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What about transparency?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Alas, you can’t edit the alpha-channel when defining colors in hexadecimal, it’s actually not possible. If ever you really want to change the opacity, you still can turn your hex triplet to a RGBa quadruplet, or use the opacity property.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Important&lt;/strong&gt;: however beware of the opacity property. It changes the opacity of the element itself, and all its child elements. Plus, it is &lt;a href=&quot;http://caniuse.com/#feat=css-opacity&quot;&gt;not supported by Internet Explorer 6, 7 and 8&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;keywords&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Keywords&lt;a href=&quot;#&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What are color keywords?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The fact is, hexadecimal is really unfriendly. Nobody knows what color is associated to a hex triplet at the first glance, because it’s a computed syntax by the machine and for the machine.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;RGB is slightly better, especially when you’re using percentage values but it’s not wonderful either. If I tell you &lt;code&gt;rgb(54%, 69%, 23%)&lt;/code&gt;, can you tell me what color it will be? Even approximately? I guess not.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That’s why there are keywords. Keywords are real color names like red, green and blue associated to actual RGB / hex triplets. Back in the days, the HTML 4.01 Standard proposed 16 different keywords:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style: none; margin-left: 0;&quot;&gt;
&lt;li style=&quot;padding: 5px; margin-bottom: 2px; background: aqua&quot;&gt;Aqua&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&quot;padding: 5px; margin-bottom: 2px; background: black; color: white&quot;&gt;Black&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&quot;padding: 5px; margin-bottom: 2px; background: blue; color: white&quot;&gt;Blue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&quot;padding: 5px; margin-bottom: 2px; background: fuchsia;&quot;&gt;Fuchsia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&quot;padding: 5px; margin-bottom: 2px; background: gray; color: white&quot;&gt;Gray&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&quot;padding: 5px; margin-bottom: 2px; background: green; color: white&quot;&gt;Green&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&quot;padding: 5px; margin-bottom: 2px; background: lime;&quot;&gt;Lime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&quot;padding: 5px; margin-bottom: 2px; background: maroon; color: white&quot;&gt;Maroon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&quot;padding: 5px; margin-bottom: 2px; background: navy; color: white&quot;&gt;Navy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&quot;padding: 5px; margin-bottom: 2px; background: olive; color: white&quot;&gt;Olive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&quot;padding: 5px; margin-bottom: 2px; background: purple; color: white&quot;&gt;Purple&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&quot;padding: 5px; margin-bottom: 2px; background: red; color: white&quot;&gt;Red&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&quot;padding: 5px; margin-bottom: 2px; background: silver;&quot;&gt;Silver&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&quot;padding: 5px; margin-bottom: 2px; background: teal; color: white&quot;&gt;Teal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&quot;padding: 5px; margin-bottom: 2px; background: white;&quot;&gt;White&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style=&quot;padding: 5px; margin-bottom: 2px; background: yellow;&quot;&gt;Yellow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then the CSS2.1 specification added the &lt;span style=&quot;background: orange; display: inline-block; padding: 0 5px;&quot;&gt;orange&lt;/span&gt; keyword. Finally, CSS3 came with 130 additional keywords for a total of 147 keywords (134 non-gray, 13 gray).
I won’t list all of them here because it would be too long however, this is a visualization of all of them on a hue wheel by &lt;a href=&quot;http://meyerweb.com/eric/css/colors/hsl-147.html&quot;&gt;Eric Meyer&lt;/a&gt; (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.xanthir.com/blog/b4JC0&quot;&gt;annotated version by Tab Atkins Jr.&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Color Wheel&quot; src=&quot;/images/css-colors__color-wheel.jpg&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of this work is to show keywords are associated to random colors: they are chosen according to their position on the hue wheel.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Eric Meyer also created a color equivalents table in order to know what keyword is associated to which color, with hexadecimal, RGB (both syntax) and HSL versions you &lt;a href=&quot;http://meyerweb.com/eric/css/colors/&quot;&gt;can find here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Keywords usage&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The point of keywords is to use basic colors with words that actually mean something. I say “basic” because most of the time, you’ll want a custom color who doesn’t have a keyword. But whenever you want to use a plain red or a silver grey, you don’t have to use a hex or RGB triplet; you can use the keyword.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;Note: the 147 keywords are all perfectly valid, even on old browsers like Internet Explorer 6.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Special keywords&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are two keywords which are a little bit special since they do not refer to a RGB triplet. Those are &lt;code&gt;transparent&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;currentColor&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Transparent&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The transparent value exists since CSS1 but was only valid as a value for the background property. Nowadays &lt;code&gt;transparent&lt;/code&gt; is a valid keyword for any property accepting a color value (color, border-color, background, shadows, gradients, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Its effect is pretty straight forward: it makes the color (or background-color or whatever) of the element transparent, as it is by default when no color is specified.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What’s the point you say? To restore the default transparent color if a color value you can’t remove is already set.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;CurrentColor&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The currentColor is a CSS3 value allowing you to take the color as a default value for another property. Have a look at the code below.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;.my-element {
color: red;
    border-color: 5px solid currentColor;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The border will be red since the defined color is red. If no color was set, it would have been black, since the default value for the color property is black.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You want to know what’s awesome? &lt;code&gt;currentColor&lt;/code&gt; is a default value for a bunch of things. From my tests:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Border-color&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Color component in box-shadow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Color component in text-shadow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It means you can do one of those and be perfectly valid:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;.my-element {
    color: red;
    border-color: 5px solid;   /* This will be red */
    box-shadow: 10px 10px 5px; /* This will be red */
    text-shadow: 0 2px 1px;    /* This will be red */
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;Note: the cap on the C letter is not required. It’s only a writing convention.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;hsl&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;HSL&lt;a href=&quot;#hsl&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What is HSL?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;HSL stands for Hue, Saturation and Lightness. Please don’t worry, HSL is not another format of color. It’s only another representation of the RGB model. This cylindric representation aims at showing the RGB model in a more intuitive way than the previous seen cube.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/css-colors__color-hsl.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Color HSL&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Hue&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The angle around the central vertical axis of the cylinder corresponds to the “hue”, which is basically the color you want. Take a chromatic wheel: at 0° you have red, at 120° you have green, at 240°you have blue and you go back to red when you reach 360°.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/css-colors__color-wheel.png&quot; alt=&quot;Color Wheel&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Saturation&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The distance from the central vertical axis of the cylinder corresponds to “saturation” (also called “chroma”). It can be understood as the quantity of black and white you add to your color. When set to 100%, the color is “pure”, but when you reduce the saturation you’re creating a “mixture”, progressively moving your color to some kind of grey.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Lightness&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The distance along the vertical axis corresponds to the “lightness” (also said “value” or “brightness”). To put it simple, the lightness is there to move your color to white or to black. When you’re making a pure color (like red, blue, orange, etc.), you’ll have lightness to 50%. If you want to darken or lighten your color without turning it into an ugly grey, then you’ll change the lightness value.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;How do we define HSL colors?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To describe a color using the HSL representation, you have to define parameters for hue, saturation and lightness. If you don’t know how to start, this is what I recommand:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hue&lt;/strong&gt;: choose your color on the chromatic wheel. If it’s red, then the value is 0. If it’s purple, the value would be about 300, and so on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Saturation&lt;/strong&gt;: if you want a pure color, then the saturation value will be 100%. If you want some kind of grey, try a value lower than 100%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lightness&lt;/strong&gt;: if you want a pure color, then the lightness value will be 50%. If you want a light color, try something between 50% and 100%. If you want something dark, try below 50%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;.white { /* I’m white! */
    color: hsl(0, 0%, 100%);
}

.black { /* I’m black! */
    color: hsl(0, 0%, 0%);
}

.red { /* I’m red! */
    color: hsl(0, 100%, 50%);
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;Note: when you want black or white, whatever the hue value you set since it’s not on the wheel. It means &lt;code&gt;hsl(0, 0%, 100%)&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;hsl(120, 0%, 100%)&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;hsl(240, 0%, 100%)&lt;/code&gt; are all 3 white.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;Note: the hue value is expressed in degrees but you don’t have to set the unit. Actually you must not set the unit; the parser won’t understand it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What about the alpha-channel?&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As for RGBa, you can set a value for the alpha-channel on a HSL color. It works exactly the same way RGBa does: it accepts a float value between 0 and 1 such as 0.56.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;.parent {
    background-image: url(‘my-picture.jpg’);
}

.child {
    background: hsla(0, 0%, 100%, 0.75);
    color: hsl(0, 0%, 30%);
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;system-colors&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;System colors&lt;a href=&quot;#system-colors&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You may or may not have heard about System colors. At first, I didn’t want to talk about them because they are deprecated in the CSS3 specification but I thought it could be interesting to drop a few lines just in a matter of curiosity.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;System colors are a little bit special since they are not matched to a RGB equivalent, at least not directly. They are keywords associated to a color related to the user’s operating system (Windows XP, Mac OS X, Linux Ubuntu, etc.) like &lt;code&gt;buttonFace&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;activeBorder&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Since the goal of CSS specifications is to standardize things, you understand why they announced System colors as deprecated. Plus, not all operating systems support all the System color keywords; basically it’s a mess.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you want a complete list of system color keywords, please refer to &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/fr/docs/CSS/color_value&quot;&gt;this documentation on Mozilla Developer Network&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;What to use when?&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Honestly, this is really up to you. In the end, a RGB triplet is generated, parsed and applied no matter the way you displayed it. The browser parser doesn’t care if you prefer &lt;code&gt;hsl(0, 100%, 50%)&lt;/code&gt; over &lt;code&gt;rgba(255, 0, 0, 1)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;/* This will be red, whatever you pick */
.red { color: red; } 
.red { color: #f00; }
.red { color: #ff0000; }
.red { color: rgb(255, 0, 0); } 
.red { color: rgb(100%, 0%, 0%); } 
.red { color: rgba(255, 0, 0, 1); }
.red { color: rgba(100%, 0%, 0%, 1); }
.red { color: hsl(0, 100%, 50%); }
.red { color: hsla(0, 100%, 50%, 1); }&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now if you want my way of doing with colors, here is what I do in most cases:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RGB&lt;/strong&gt;: by itself, I don’t use RGB since I usually use a color picker giving me hex triplet. But when I need to edit the alpha-channel, I use RGBa of course.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hexadecimal&lt;/strong&gt;: this is what I use the most in real projects. As said above, any web color picker on the internet will give you at least a hex code. It’s kind of the standard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keywords&lt;/strong&gt;: I use them either for demos when I don’t care much about the color I pick, or for greyscale like white, black and silver.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HSL&lt;/strong&gt;: I never use HSL because I’m not used to it. It’s a really really good representation of the RGB model but it doesn’t look very intuitive to me so I stick with RGB.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What I think is really cool with HSL however is the fact you can get a shade instead of another color by tweaking the lightness. This is a thing you can’t do with other syntaxes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;preprocessors&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Colors ands CSS preprocessors&lt;a href=&quot;#preprocessors&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;CSS preprocessors (at least some of them) provide built-in functions to play with colors. Things like saturate, darken, hue rotation and such. Let me introduce some of them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;LESS (&lt;a href=&quot;http://lesscss.org/#-color-functions&quot;&gt;doc&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;lighten(@color, @percentage);               /* Makes lighter */
darken(@color, @percentage);                /* Makes darker */

saturate(@color, @percentage);              /* Makes more saturated*/
desaturate(@color, @percentage);            /* Makes less saturated*/

fadein(@color, @percentage);                /* Makes more opaque */
fadeout(@color, @percentage);               /* Makes more transparent */ 
fade(@color, @percentage);                  /* Gives the color 50% opacity */

spin(@color, @degrees);                     /* Rotates the hue wheel 10° */

mix(@color1, @color2, @percentage);         /* Mixes 2 colors with a default weight of 50% */
contrast(@color1, @darkcolor, @lightcolor); /* Returns @darkcolor if the color is &gt;50% luma (i.e. is a light color) otherwise return @lightcolor */&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Sass (&lt;a href=&quot;http://sass-lang.com/docs/yardoc/Sass/Script/Functions.html&quot;&gt;doc&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;rgba($color, $alpha)               /* Convert a hex color into a RGBa one */
red($color)                        /* Gets the red component */
green($color)                      /* Gets the green component */
blue($color)                       /* Gets the blue component */
mix($color-1, $color-2, [$weight]) /* Mixes 2 colors together with a default weight of 50% */

hue($color)                         /* Gets the hue component */
saturation($color)                  /* Gets the saturation component */
lightness($color)                   /* Gets the lightness component */
adjust-hue($color, $degrees)        /* Rotates the hue wheel */
lighten($color, $percentage)        /* Makes lighter */
darken($color, $percentage)         /* Makes darker */
saturate($color, $percentage)       /* Makes more saturated */
desaturate($color, $percentage)     /* Makes less saturated */

grayscale($color)                   /* Converts to grayscale */
complement($color)                  /* Returns the complement */
invert($color)                      /* Returns the inverse */

alpha($color)                       /* Gets the alpha component (opacity) */
opacity($color)                     /* Gets the alpha component (opacity) */
opacify($color, $percentage)        /* Makes more opaque */
fade-in($color, $percentage)        /* Makes more opaque */
transparentize($color, $percentage) /* Makes more transparent */
fade-out($color, $percentage)       /* Makes more transparent */&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;CSS Crush (&lt;a href=&quot;http://the-echoplex.net/csscrush/&quot;&gt;doc&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;h-adjust($color $value)             /* Rotates the hue wheel */
s-adjust($color $value)             /* Changes the saturation */
l-adjust($color $value)             /* Changes the lightness */
a-adjust($color $value)             /* Changes the alpha-channel */&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Stylus (&lt;a href=&quot;http://learnboost.github.com/stylus/docs/bifs.html&quot;&gt;doc&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/h3&gt;




&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;red(color)          /* Gets the red component */
green(color)        /* Gets the green component */
blue(color)         /* Gets the blue component */
alpha(color)        /* Gets the alpha component */

dark(color)         /* Makes lighter */
light(color)        /* Makes darker */
hue(color)          /* Gets the hue component */
saturation(color)   /* Gets the saturation component */
lightness(color)    /* Gets the lightness component */&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;final-words&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Final words&lt;a href=&quot;#final-words&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As I was documenting myself to write this article, I understood color stuff is very complicated either in optical, in paint or in digital. Those notions of “hex triplet”, “chromatic wheel”, “base 16”, “alpha” are so abstract we can face some difficulties to understand what they mean, what they represent.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thankfully in CSS we don’t have to use a base 16 converter everytime we want to describe a color. Tools do it for us. But this is a really interesting topic, so I’d recommand you read about it. You’d be surprise how huge it can be!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, back to CSS, let me (re)introduce you a few awesome tools and resources to help you deal with colors:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fr.slideshare.net/maxdesign/css3-colors&quot;&gt;CSS3 Colors slides&lt;/a&gt; by Russ Weakley&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://css.coloratum.com/&quot;&gt;CSS Coloratum&lt;/a&gt;, a color converter by Lea Verou&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://tympanus.net/codrops/2012/09/17/build-a-color-scheme-the-fundamentals/&quot;&gt;Build a color scheme: the fundamentals&lt;/a&gt; by Patrick Cox&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://tympanus.net/codrops/2012/11/26/using-transparency-in-web-design-dos-and-donts/&quot;&gt;Using transparency in webdesign: dos and don'ts&lt;/a&gt; by Carrie Cousins&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://tympanus.net/codrops/2012/02/28/principles-of-color-and-the-color-wheel/&quot; title=&quot;Principles of Color and the Color Wheel&quot;&gt;Principles or Color and the Color Wheel&lt;/a&gt; by Carrie Cousins&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://kuler.adobe.com/&quot;&gt;Kuler&lt;/a&gt; by Adobe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://colorschemedesigner.com/&quot;&gt;Color Scheme Designer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://0to255.com/&quot;&gt;0to255&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://meyerweb.com/eric/css/colors/&quot;&gt;Color Equivalents Table&lt;/a&gt; by Eric Meyer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.xanthir.com/blog/b4JC0&quot;&gt;CSS Color Keyword Distribution&lt;/a&gt; by Tab Atkins Jr. (&lt;a href=&quot;http://meyerweb.com/eric/css/colors/hsl-147.html&quot;&gt;original work&lt;/a&gt; by Eric Meyer)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://colour.charlottedann.com/&quot;&gt;Official Brand Colors&lt;/a&gt; by Charlotte Dann&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thanks a lot for reading this article. If you have any question or feedback, please be sure to share. Also, if you find any mistake, I'd be glad to correct it. ;)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 27 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/11/27/css-colors/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/11/27/css-colors/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>A CSS challenge</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday night, I've seen something in my Twitter timeline which excited my curiosity: a CSS challenge. It was proposed by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/goetter&quot;&gt;Raphael Goetter&lt;/a&gt;, a famous French front-end developer on &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.goetter.fr/post/36084887039/tes-pas-cap-premiere-edition&quot; title=&quot;CSS challenge on Raphael Goetter's blog&quot;&gt;his blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Since I'm sure you'll be interested in a little CSS riddle (you will, will you?), let me tell you what this is about.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/fZkkw.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;CSS challenge&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will you be able to do this (I'm talking about the small line behind the text) following the restrictions below?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only one single element (&lt;code&gt;h1&lt;/code&gt;) in the body element&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Element horizontally centered in its parent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The line is vertically centered on the text&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Both the font size and the text have to be editable without having to edit the line&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Body and/or the element can have a background (image) without changing anything else&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No HTTP request, no image, no JavaScript&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The best browser support the better of course&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I can't wait to see the way you'll figure this out guys. I personally found something with a few downsides sadly. I'm sure some of you will be able to find a kick-ass solution. ;)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;solutions&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;[Edit] Solutions (November 24th, 2012)&lt;a href=&quot;#solutions&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thanks for participating! There have been a couple of answers for this trick. Druid of Lûhn proposed &lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io/Druid-of-Luhn/details/sclvk&quot;&gt;something&lt;/a&gt; which works but sadly it's pretty awful for SEO since it involves an empty &lt;code&gt;h1&lt;/code&gt; tag.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Joshua Hibbert &lt;a href=&quot;http://jsfiddle.net/joshnh/3PG8j/&quot;&gt;used linear gradients&lt;/a&gt; to do it (so &lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io/raphaelgoetter/pen/dGxvL&quot;&gt;did&lt;/a&gt; Raphael Goetter). This is a clever technique I thought about but didn't give a try. My experience with gradients is not that good.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here is the way I &lt;a href=&quot;http://jsfiddle.net/HugoGiraudel/cyeGM/1/&quot;&gt;did it&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;body {
    text-align: center;
    overflow: hidden;
    background: #ffa;
}

h1 {
    display: -moz-inline-box;
    display: inline-block;
    *display: inline;
    *zoom: 1;
    position: relative;
    font-size: 30px;
    margin-top: 20px;
}

h1:after,
h1:before {
    content: &quot;&quot;;
    position: absolute;
    height: 1px;
    width: 1000px;
    top: 50%;
    right: 100%;
    background: black;
}

h1:after { left: 100%; }&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So basically, I used both pseudo-elements to create the line. To place them, I set the title to inline-block, and the parent (&lt;code&gt;body&lt;/code&gt;) text-align to center.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sadly, a few things suck with this technique, even if it works pretty well:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Parent needs to have &lt;code&gt;text-align: center&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Parent needs to have &lt;code&gt;overflow: auto&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It requires 2 pseudo-elements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pseudo-elements need to have a large width to reach the edge of the screen (~1000px to cover about all screen sizes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hopefully the browser support is pretty good, at least way better than the gradient version:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IE8+&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Firefox 2+&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chrome&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Safari 3+&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opera 9+&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;iOS Safari 3+&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opera Mini 5+&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Android Browser 2+&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blackberry browser 7+&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opera Mobile 10+&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chrome for Android&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Firefox for Android&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But since it's only a tiny design improvement, I'll definitely go with the gradient version on a live project. Thanks for participating. I'll try to drop another challenge soon. :)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/11/20/css-challenge/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/11/20/css-challenge/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>Learning principles for improving your CSS</title>
				<description>
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/11/20/codrops-improve-css/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/11/20/codrops-improve-css/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>A round-up on CSS playgrounds</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;section id=&quot;playground&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What is a code playground?&lt;a href=&quot;#playground&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A code playground is an online tool allowing you to do some code, then save and share it. It's often used for quick demos and reduced testcases. It's a good alternative to the old .html file with its embedded &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;style&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;script&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tags.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Playgrounds are becoming more and more popular and there are a bunch of options when you want to use one. Let me introduce you the most popular ones:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io&quot; title=&quot;CodePen&quot;&gt;CodePen&lt;/a&gt; from Chris Coyier, Tim Sabat and Alex Vasquez&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dabblet.com&quot; title=&quot;Dabblet&quot;&gt;Dabblet&lt;/a&gt; from Lea Verou&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cssdeck.com&quot; title=&quot;CSSDeck&quot;&gt;CSSDeck&lt;/a&gt; from Rishabh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://jsfiddle.net&quot; title=&quot;JSFiddle&quot;&gt;JSFiddle&lt;/a&gt; from Oskar Krawczyk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, they all do more or less the same stuff but each one has its own strengths and weaknesses. So in the end the choice is up to the user. I'd like to give you my opinion on this stuff but first, let's make a little round-up.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;dabblet&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Dabblet&lt;a href=&quot;#dabblet&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Dabblet is an amazing playground&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: line-through;&quot;&gt;, however it doesn't support JavaScript. That being said, its author presented Dabblet as a pure CSS playground, so it's not very surprising JavaScript isn't supported&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What is a little bit more surprising however is that Dabblet doesn't provide any support for preprocessors, especially CSS ones. Nowadays, it's a pretty big deal when a playground doesn't allow users to code with preprocessors.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Plus, it seems to be very buggy sometimes. Shortcuts don't work as expected, cursor is boucing to the top of your document, etc. It's too bad because it has a minimalist and cute interface.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Pros&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Live reload&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prefixfree by default (removable)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modulable interface&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User accounts via GitHub: gallery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Cons&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: line-through&quot;&gt;No JS support&lt;/span&gt; JS tab now in alpha stage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No preprocessors support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cloned GitHub user accounts (followers/following GitHub users)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes very buggy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Resources&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dabblet.com&quot; title=&quot;Dabblet&quot;&gt;Dabblet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.dabblet.com/&quot; title=&quot;Blog Dabblet&quot;&gt;Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dabblet&quot; title=&quot;Dabblet on Twitter&quot;&gt;Dabblet&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;jsfiddle&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;JSFiddle&lt;a href=&quot;#jsfiddle&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;JSFiddle is a wonderful playground when it comes to JavaScript development since it provides a wide range of JavaScript libraries, probably more than you'll ever need. Problem is it doesn't use a live reload system meaning you have to hit &quot;Run&quot; everytime you make a change. It's kind of annoying, but for JavaScript prototyping, it's amazing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Pros&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;22 JavaScript libraries available + multiple versions: Mootools, jQuery, Prototype, YUI, Glow, Dojo, Processing.js, ExtJS, Raphael, RightJS, Three.js, Zepto, Eny, Shipyard, Knockout, The X Toolkit, AngularJS, Ember, Underscore, Bonsai, KineticJS, FabricJS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Highly customizable for JS development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Built-in options for Normalize.css&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preprocessors: SCSS (CSS), CoffeeScript (JS), JavaScript 1.7 (JS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy embedding of external stylesheets / JS scripts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Doctype accessible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Numbers versions of your work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User accounts: gallery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mobile debugger&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Cons&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No live reload&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No HTML preprocessors support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No built-in option for Prefixfree and Modernizr&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interface somewhat a bit fixed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Resources&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://jsfiddle.net&quot; title=&quot;JSFiddle&quot;&gt;JSFiddle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jsfiddle&quot; title=&quot;JSFiddle on Twitter&quot;&gt;JSFiddle&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jsfiddlesupport&quot; title=&quot;JSFiddleSupport on Twitter&quot;&gt;JSFiddleSupport&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;cssdeck&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;CSSDeck&lt;a href=&quot;#cssdeck&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;CSSDeck is fairly new in the playground scene but it's the only one providing the ability to record your code while you type it in order to have some kind of video. Basically, you can make video tutorial with CSSDeck, which you can't do with other playgrounds.&lt;/P&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Pros&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Live reload&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Codecast feature (video coding)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11 JavaScript libraries available: MooTools, jQuery, jQuery Mobile, Prototype, YUI, Underscore, Backbone, Modernizr, Sencha Touch, Dojo, Bootstrap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preprocessors: ZenCoding (HTML), Markdown (HTML), Slim (HTML), Jade (HTML), HAML (HTML), LESS (CSS), Stylus (CSS), SCSS (CSS), Sass (CSS), Compass (CSS), CoffeeScript (JS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Built-in options for Prefixfree and Normalize.css&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User accounts via Twitter or GitHub: gallery, likes &amp; follow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Possibility to make private stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Cons&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small community&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interface sometimes a bit messy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Resources&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cssdeck.com&quot; title=&quot;CSSDeck&quot;&gt;CSSDeck&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/cssdeck&quot; title=&quot;CSSDeck on Twitter&quot;&gt;CSSDeck&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;codepen&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;CodePen&lt;a href=&quot;#codepen&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;CodePen is one hell of a playground. It provides very strong tools for each of the 3 supported languages and provides awesome features for registered users like personal gallery, tags, forks, likes and follows, various themes, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Plus, authors pick best pens on the site and feature them on the front page. This way you can have a look at best front-end works outhere without having to search in thousands of pages.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Pros&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Live reload&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8 JavaScript libraries available: jQuery, jQuery UI, Zepto, MooTools, Prototype, YUI, ExtJS, Dojo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preprocessors: ZenCoding (HTML), Markdown (HTML), Slim (HTML), HAML (HTML), LESS (CSS), SCSS (CSS), Sass (CSS), CoffeeScript (JS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Built-in options for Prefixfree, Normalize.css, Reset.css and Modernizr&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; accessible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy embedding of external stylesheets / JS scripts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User accounts via GitHub: gallery, likes &amp; follow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Various themes available&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tags&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Possibility to fork&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Homepage featuring coolest pens&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A PRO version with special features (teach mode, pair programming and much more)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Cons&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interface somewhat a bit fixed (preview with small height)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everything is public without PRO version&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not registered pens are quickly deleted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes buggy with for loops&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Resources&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io&quot; title=&quot;CodePen&quot;&gt;CodePen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.codepen.io/&quot; title=&quot;CodePen blog&quot;&gt;Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/codepen&quot; title=&quot;CodePen on Twitter&quot;&gt;CodePen&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;opinion&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What's my opinion&lt;a href=&quot;#opinion&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Honestly, I think &lt;strong&gt;CodePen is far ahead of any other playground outhere&lt;/strong&gt;. All in all, it provides more options than others, it's more stable, less buggy, and far more popular even if it's only 6 months old.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I used to work a lot in Dabblet but I've always found those tiny little bugs very annoying. Then I switched to JSFiddle but the lack of a live reload was bothering me. Then came CodePen and it was kind of a revelation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Shortly after the launch, I spent a huge amount of time on CodePen to play with CSS. Back in the days, I did between 1 and 5 pens a day (inspired from Dribbble), most of them hitting the front page. It was very amusing. Now, I'm not doing much anymore because I use my free time for Codrops as part of articles.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, if you'd like to have a glance behind the scenes of CodePen, &lt;a href=&quot;http://davidwalsh.name/codepen-interview&quot; title=&quot;CodePen interview&quot;&gt;David Walsh recently interviewed Chris Coyier about it&lt;/a&gt;. They talk about challenges to get there, technical details and of course what's planned for the future.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've made a comparison of these 4 playgrounds as a table for more clarity. Here is &lt;a href=&quot;http://jsfiddle.net/FDDed/13/embedded/result/&quot; title=&quot;Comparison CSS playgrounds&quot;&gt;the JSFiddle&lt;/a&gt;. Yeah, I made a &lt;strong&gt;JSFiddle&lt;/strong&gt;, because on CodePen everything is public, and I don't want to drop those kind of things there. It's probably one of the only bad sides of CodePen, which will be soon gone.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;iframe style=&quot;width: 100%; height: 500px; margin: 20px 0;&quot; src=&quot;http://jsfiddle.net/FDDed/13/embedded/result/&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;allowfullscreen&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What about you? What's your favorite CSS playground?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/11/19/css-playgrounds/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/11/19/css-playgrounds/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>One week, first changes</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;section id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Design&lt;a href=&quot;#design&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After the launch, it occured to me the design was a bit gloomy so I wanted to add a color to cheer things up. After a dark blue and a creepy green, I ended with the hot pink and a quick survey on Twitter encouraged me to keep it. So pink it is! Hope you like it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Speaking of survey, another quick one about text align told me to switch to left. It looks like people dislike when text is justified on blogs. I liked it but I'm not the main reader of this blog. :D&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;development&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Development&lt;a href=&quot;#development&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was playing with &lt;a href=&quot;http://sass-lang.com/&quot; title=&quot;Sass&quot;&gt;Sass&lt;/a&gt; during the last couple of days and decided it could be cool to build the blog on it, so now it is. Since the site is pretty small, it's no big deal. Actually I used only very few of the potential of Sass (or whatever other CSS preprocessor):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Variables&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nested styles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A few mixins&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Concatenation and minification of the stylesheets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, it's cool.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;features&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Features&lt;a href=&quot;#features&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Prism.js as a syntax highlighter&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You may have also noticed I've included &lt;a href=&quot;http://prismjs.com/&quot; title=&quot;Prism&quot;&gt;Prism.js&lt;/a&gt; from Lea Verou on the blog as a syntax highlighter for code snippets. I'm pretty happy with it, I think it makes the code easier to read.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Only issue I see right now with Prism.js is it has some issues with processed CSS syntax such as LESS and Sass, but it's no big deal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Disqus as a comment system&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To satisfy a few requests, I agreed on setting up a comment system to allow you to say stuff. Since I decided I won't do any PHP on the site, I had only a few if not one option. Hopefully &lt;a href=&quot;http://disqus.com/&quot; title=&quot;Disqus&quot;&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt; is widely spread all around the world now and honestly I would have never done such a wonder so I'm pretty excited about it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Depending on how things go I'll have a closer look into options but for now it's far better than anything I would have ever hope for so I'm very happy with it. Then please drop a comment if you have anything to tell. ;)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Codrops articles notifications&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You may or may not have noticed yet but from now on, my articles on Codrops will be featured on the &lt;a href=&quot;index.html&quot; title=&quot;Index blog&quot;&gt;index of the blog&lt;/a&gt;. To distinguish them from other articles, they are annotated with &lt;i class=&quot;icon-tint&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;codrops&quot;&gt;[Codrops]&lt;/span&gt;. What do you think? Good idea? Bad idea?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;to-do&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;To do&lt;a href=&quot;#to-do&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I've already made a bunch of tiny bug fixes like broken links, inadequate margins, little issues on mobile but some bugs may persist so if you still find one, please tell me: I'll fix it as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you have any suggestion to how we could make this place better, please feel free to speak. By the way I'd like to thanks all of you giving feedbacks and helping me improve this place. It means a lot, keep up! :)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 15 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/11/15/one-week-first-changes/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/11/15/one-week-first-changes/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>Creative CSS loading animations</title>
				<description>
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 14 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/11/14/codrops-css-animations/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/11/14/codrops-css-animations/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>Why I switched from LESS to Sass</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yaaay, another blog post on the web about CSS preprocessors, as if there wasn’t enough. Don’t worry: I won’t try to convince you to use a CSS preprocessor, neither about the one you should pick. These decisions are really up to you.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So this post will be about my own experience with CSS preprocessors. For the concern, I recently wrote an article for Codrops untitled “10 things I learnt about CSS” and I talked a lot about preprocessors, so I’ve read (and tried) a bunch of things on the topic lately.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway and before anything, please note I’m not a hardcore CSS preprocessor user. I’m more like a novice with these tools, but I’ve already worked a little bit on 2 of them: firstly LESS then Sass. I recently moved from LESS to Sass and don’t plan on going back.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;why-less-as-a-first-try&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why LESS as a first try&lt;a href=&quot;#why-less-as-a-first-try&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I wanted to have a real shot with CSS preprocessors after hours of playing on &lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io&quot;&gt;CodePen&lt;/a&gt; so I read a few things to make a choice. To put it simple, there are currently 4 major CSS preprocessors:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://sass-lang.com/&quot; title=&quot;Sass&quot;&gt;Sass&lt;/a&gt; built on Ruby&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lesscss.org/&quot; title=&quot;LESS&quot;&gt;LESS&lt;/a&gt; built on JavaScript&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://learnboost.github.com/stylus/&quot; title=&quot;Stylus&quot;&gt;Stylus&lt;/a&gt; built on JavaScript&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://the-echoplex.net/csscrush/&quot; title=&quot;CSS Crush&quot;&gt;CSS Crush&lt;/a&gt; built on PHP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve never heard much about Stylus so it was not an option to me. I wanted to have a quick access to complete documentation since I was a little bit scared to take the plunge. And even if CSS Crush sounded really cool because I’m familiar with PHP, I’ve read too few on it to consider this as real choice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I had to choose between LESS and Sass like almost everyone else. One thing made the difference in favor of LESS: it could run locally. You see I’m more like a client-side kind of guy. I’m really uncomfortable when it comes to server and command lines, so the fact LESS could be compiled with JavaScript on the fly sounded awesome to me. On the other hand, Sass required to install Ruby and run some command lines and it scared me. So LESS it was.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve played with LESS a few days, tried a few things and even built my own framework on it. It was really cool to see CSS pushed to an upper level and I was starting to think I could do all my future projects with LESS. Until I realized LESS client-side compilation is awful performance speaking.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, that wasn’t the worst thing. I still could learn how to run the server-side part of LESS to compile, or switch to LESSPHP with the help of my brother who uses it at work. No, the worst thing occurred to me when I tried to dig deep down into the entrails of LESS.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;when-i-started-realizing-less-wasnt-the-eldorado&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;When I started realizing LESS wasn’t the Eldorado&lt;a href=&quot;#when-i-started-realizing-less-wasnt-the-eldorado&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the first “complicated” thing I tried to create was a mixin handling CSS arrows the same way &lt;a href=&quot;http://cssarrowplease.com/&quot; title=&quot;CSSArrowPlease&quot;&gt;CSSArrowPlease&lt;/a&gt; does. It took me a couple of hours but I finally succeeded and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/HugoGiraudel/LESS-Mixin-for-CSS-arrows&quot; title=&quot;LESS Mixin for CSS arrows&quot;&gt;hosted it on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. However I noticed something counter-intuitive: conditional statements.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;LESS and conditional statements&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The way I wanted to handle my mixin was something which would look like this:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;.mixin(parameters) {
/* Basic stuff here */
if (direction = top)    { /* Conditional stuff here */ }
else if (direction = bottom) { /* Conditional stuff here */ }
else if (direction = left)   { /* Conditional stuff here */ }
else if (direction = right)  { /* Conditional stuff here */ }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The fact is &lt;strong&gt;LESS doesn’t handle if / else statements&lt;/strong&gt;. Instead, it provides guarded mixins (mixin when a parameter exists or equals / is inferior / is superior to something). So basically, I had to do something like this:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;.mixin(parameters) {
    /*Basic stuff here */
}
.mixin(parameters) when (direction = top) {
    /* Conditional stuff here */
}
.mixin(parameters) when (direction = bottom) {
    /* Conditional stuff here */
}
.mixin(parameters) when (direction = left) {
    /* Conditional stuff here */
}
.mixin(parameters) when (direction = right) {
    /* Conditional stuff here */
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It may look similar at the first glance but it involves a few things:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it multiplies the number of mixin declarations. It’s not one mixin with conditions, it’s multiple mixins varying according to their parameters,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it becomes hard to understand when multiple conditions are gathered at once,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it looks counter-intuitive to me since I would like to do as mentioned earlier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I was just a little frustrated not to be able to use what seems intuitive to me: real if/else conditional statements but all in all I succeeded in doing my mixin so it was not so bad. Things started getting bad when I wanted to do moar.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For a recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://tympanus.net/codrops/2012/11/14/creative-css-loading-animations/&quot; title=&quot;Creative CSS loading animations&quot;&gt;Codrops article on pure CSS loading animations&lt;/a&gt;, I wanted to include a few things about CSS preprocessors and how they are supposed to be easy to use. Actually, it could have been very very simple if I wasn’t using LESS. One of these things was a loop.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;LESS and loops&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Loops are cool: they can handle a huge amount of operations in only a few lines and even if you don’t need them everyday in CSS, it’s cool to have the option to use them. I wanted a loop to set the appropriate animation name on a dozen of elements. This is more or less what I was expecting:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;@nbElements: 10;
for(@i = 0; @i &amp;lt; @nbElements; @i++) {
    .my-element:nth-child(@i) { animation-name: loading-@i; }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, this is absolutely not how LESS is handling loops. Actually &lt;strong&gt;LESS doesn't handle loops&lt;/strong&gt;; you have to use a recursive function (a function calling itself) in order to reproduce the desired behaviour. This is what I ended up with:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;/* Define loop */
.loop(@index) when (@index &amp;gt; 0) {
    (~&quot;.my-element:nth-child(@{index})&quot;) {
        animation-name: &quot;loading-@{index}&quot;;
    }

    /* Call itself */
    .loop(@index - 1);
}

/* Stop loop */
.loop (0) {}

/* Use loop */
@nbElements: 10;
.loop (@nbElements);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In what universe is this more user-friendly and intuitive than a classic for loop? Is there anyone here who would have thought about this at first? I started thinking LESS was not as perfect as I first thought but sadly, that was still not the worst part.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Things went very ugly when I wanted to manage @keyframes inside this for loop. Yeah, I know: I like challenge.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;LESS and concatenation&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I know concatenation can be somewhat annoying to handle depending on the language, but I was far from thinking LESS was so bad on this topic. First thing I discovered: &lt;strong&gt;you can't use/concatenate a variable as a selector&lt;/strong&gt; without a work-around and &lt;strong&gt;you absolutely can't use a variable as a property name&lt;/strong&gt; in LESS (at least as far as I can tell). Only as a value.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;/* This works */
.my-element {
    color: @my-value;
}

/* This doesn't work */
@my-element {
    color: @my-value;
}

/* This doesn't work either */
@{my-element} {
    color: @my-value;
}

/* But this works */
(~&quot;@{my-element}&quot;) {
    color: @my-value;
}

/* And this can't work */
.my-element {
    @my-property: @my-value;
    @{my-property}: @my-value;
    (~&quot;@{my-property}&quot;): @my-value;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Two very annoying things there: we definitely can't use variables as property names and the concatenation syntax is ugly as hell. &lt;code&gt;(~&quot;@{variable}&quot;)&lt;/code&gt;, really? But actually if you want my opinion, &lt;strong&gt;the biggest mistake they made is to name variables with the at sign @&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is somewhat well thought out since CSS is using this sign for “alternative stuff” like media queries (@media), animation keyframes (@keyframes) and probably other things in the future (@page for example). I got the reasoning and I admire the will of sticking to the regular CSS syntax.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But come on... How come they didn’t think about variable concatenations and @keyframes/@page uses inside mixins?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Basically, LESS fails to understand @page and @keyframes inside mixins because it throws an exception according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/cloudhead/less.js/blob/b235734a11f646252db8f0947fee406ce67cf904/lib/less/parser.js#L1158&quot; title=&quot;Source LESS&quot;&gt;its source code&lt;/a&gt;. So you'll need two nested mixins: one handling your animation, the second one to handle the keyframes. Sounds heavy and complicated, well it is. So let’s say you want to create a custom mixin using @keyframes and vendor prefixes (not much, right?) this is what you have to do:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;@newline: `&quot;\n&quot;`; /* Newline */
.my-mixin(@selector, @name, @other-parameters) {
    /* @selector is the element using your animation 
     * @name is the name of your animation
     * @other-parameters are the parameters of your animation
     */ 

    .keyframe-mixin(@pre, @post, @vendor) {
        /* @pre is the newline hack (empty on the first declaration)
         * @post is a variable fix to detect the last declaration (1 on the last one)
         * @vendor is the vendor prefix you want  
         */

        (~&quot;@{pre}@@{vendor}keyframes @{name} {@{newline} 0%&quot;) {
            /* 0% stuff here */ 
        } 

        100%  { 
            /* 100% stuff here */
        } 

        .Local(){}
        .Local() when (@post=1) {
            (~&quot;}@{newline}@{selector}&quot;) {
                -webkit-animation: @name;
                -moz-animation:    @name;
                -ms-animation:     @name;
                -o-animation:      @name;
                animation:         @name;
            } 
        }    
    .Local;
    }

.keyframe-mixin(&quot;&quot;            , 0, &quot;-webkit-&quot;);
.keyframe-mixin(~&quot;}@{newline}&quot;, 0,    &quot;-moz-&quot;);
.keyframe-mixin(~&quot;}@{newline}&quot;, 0,     &quot;-ms-&quot;);
.keyframe-mixin(~&quot;}@{newline}&quot;, 0,      &quot;-o-&quot;);
.keyframe-mixin(~&quot;}@{newline}&quot;, 1,         &quot;&quot;);

} 
.my-mixin(&quot;#whatever&quot;, name, other-parameters);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yeah, this is a complete nightmare. I'm not the one who wrote this; I've been searching for hours how to do this before finding &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/13160991/chaining-keyframe-attributes-with-less&quot; title=&quot;Chaining keyframe attributes with LESS&quot;&gt;a very complete answer&lt;/a&gt; on StackOverflow leading to two others related topic with wonderful answers (&lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/11551313/less-css-pass-mixin-as-a-parameter-to-another-mixin/11589227#11589227&quot; title=&quot;Mixin as a parameter to another mixin&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/9166152/sign-and-variables-in-css-keyframes-using-less-css&quot; title=&quot;Sign and variables in CSS keyframes using LESS CSS&quot;&gt;there&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;Note: the &lt;code&gt;.Local()&lt;/code&gt; thing seems to be a keyword for &quot;this&quot; but I couldn't find any confirmation on this. If you have, please catch me on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So basically, here is what there is to say (&lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/9166152/sign-and-variables-in-css-keyframes-using-less-css/11028622#11028622&quot; title=&quot;Sign and variables in CSS keyframes using LESS CSS&quot;&gt;still not from me&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The initial selector &lt;code&gt;(~&quot;@keyframes @{name}{&quot;) { ... }&lt;/code&gt; renders as &lt;code&gt;@keyframes name { { ... }&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;   
&lt;li&gt;To avoid &lt;code&gt;{ {&lt;/code&gt;, it requires a newline which cannot be escaped directly so through the variable &lt;code&gt;@newline: `&quot;\n&quot;`;&lt;/code&gt;. LESS parses anything between backticks as JavaScript, so the resulting value is a newline character.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since &lt;code&gt;{ ... }&lt;/code&gt; requires a selector to be valid, we use the first step of the animation (0%).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But the curly braces do not match. To fix this, we can add a dummy selector in the end, which starts with &lt;code&gt;(~&quot;} dummy&quot;) { .. }&lt;/code&gt;. How ugly is that?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But wait, we already know that vendor prefixes are going to be added in sequel. So, let the final first selector be &lt;code&gt;(~&quot;@{pre} @@{vendor}keyframes @{name} {@{newline}0%&quot;)&lt;/code&gt;. What a nightmare...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;@{pre}&lt;/code&gt; has to be &lt;code&gt;&quot;}@{newline}&quot;&lt;/code&gt; for every keyframes block after the first one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instead of a dummy selector for the last curly brace, we define the keyframe mixins. We're using a guarded mixin to implement this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this was waaaaay too much for me. &lt;strong&gt;The point of CSS preprocessors is to easy the CSS development, not to make it harder&lt;/strong&gt;. So this is the moment I realized LESS wasn't &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; good.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;why-i-think-sass-is-better&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why I think Sass is better&lt;a href=&quot;#why-i-think-sass-is-better&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I won't make a complete and detailed comparison between Sass and LESS because some guys did it very well already (&lt;a href=&quot;http://css-tricks.com/sass-vs-less/&quot; title=&quot;Sass vs LESS&quot;&gt;Chris Coyier&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://fr.slideshare.net/utbkevin/less-vs-sass-css-precompiler-showdown-14068991&quot; title=&quot;LESS vs SASS CSS precompiler showdown&quot;&gt;Kewin Powell&lt;/a&gt;, etc.). I'll only cover the few points I talked about earlier.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Sass and conditional statements&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;@mixin my-mixin($parameters) {
    /* Basic stuff here */
    @if $my-parameter == value {
        /* Conditional stuff here */
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is the Sass syntax for conditional statements in a mixin. Okay, it may lack of some brackets but it's way easier than the LESS syntax in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Sass and loops&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;@for $i from 1 through 10 {
/* My stuff here */
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Once again, it may lack of a few brackets but we still understand very well how it works. It's almost plain language: &lt;em&gt;&quot;for variable i from 1 through 10, do this&quot;&lt;/em&gt;. It looks very intuitive to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Sass and concatenation&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sass has absolutely no problem with concatenation neither in selectors nor in property names. You only have to do this &lt;code&gt;#{$my-variable}&lt;/code&gt; to make things work.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;#{$my-selector} {
    #{$my-property}: $my-value;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Other things&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Very quickly, here are the few things making me tell Sass is better than LESS. Those are well explained in the above links.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sass has &lt;a href=&quot;http://compass-style.org/&quot; title=&quot;Compass&quot;&gt;Compass&lt;/a&gt; which keeps CSS3 support up to date&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sass provides the &lt;code&gt;@extend&lt;/code&gt; feature allowing you to extend a class from another one&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sass handles media queries in a better and more advanced ways than others&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sass throws errors instead of miscalculations when doing operations with units&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: line-through;&quot;&gt;Sass provides a minifying function to compress your CSS files&lt;/span&gt; (so does LESS server-side)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sass is slightly more active, development speaking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;less-is-not-so-bad&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;LESS is not so bad&lt;a href=&quot;#less-is-not-so-bad&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, I've been moaning about LESS the whole article, but honestly this is not so bad. At least, it's no so bad if you don't plan on complicated and advanced things. Actually there are things LESS are better at, let me tell you my opinion about it:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: line-through;&quot;&gt;LESS provides some really cool color functions (darken, lighten, spin, de/saturate, fade, fadein, fadeout, mix, contrast)&lt;/span&gt; (so does Sass)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LESS has a nicer and more accessible documentation on &lt;a href=&quot;http://lesscss.org/&quot; title=&quot;LESS&quot;&gt;lesscss.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LESS is not dependent to either command line skills or a third program&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LESS can be used locally without any install required (simple JS script)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.github.com/bootstrap/&quot; title=&quot;Twitter Bootstrap&quot;&gt;Twitter Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt; which is probably the biggest framework outhere running thousands of websites is built on LESS; it sounds like a nice proof that LESS is a good CSS preprocessor to me&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Whatsoever, the choice is really up to you. All of this was only my opinion based on my experience. &lt;strong&gt;LESS is still a good CSS preprocessor, but in the end I think Sass is simply better&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 13 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/11/13/less-to-sass/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/11/13/less-to-sass/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>Hugogiraudel.com redesigned + new blog</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi guys! As you can see, I have big news. I've changed a few things on hugogiraudel.com in order to make it look like a little bit more aesthetic and/or professionnal. What do you say?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Actually, this is the very recent redesign of &lt;a href=&quot;http://daverupert.com&quot; title=&quot;Dave Rupert&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;http://daverupert.com&lt;/a&gt; (nice job by the way) who led me to do such a task. You see, for months (almost years!) and I don't really know why, I thought I had to manage a CMS like WordPress or whatever to handle a blog. But why bother? Simple HTML/CSS pushing on a server and this is done, right?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;what-for&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;A blog, what for?&lt;a href=&quot;#what-for&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a good question since I'm not planning on heavy blogging. You may know I'm a writer for &lt;a href=&quot;http://tympanus.net/codrops/&quot; title=&quot;Codrops&quot;&gt;Codrops&lt;/a&gt; and hell I'm proud of it. Anyway, it takes me a good amount of time, so I won't be able to post things everyday here.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;However, I really wanted a place on the internet to talk about some things I can't write about at Codrops. I'm still talking about web, don't worry. Things like tools, personal experiences, stuff about my work, my side projects, or whatever.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;functioning&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;How does this work?&lt;a href=&quot;#functioning&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Actually this is very simple for now, but I'm planning on a few things to improve my workflow in a not so far future. As of today, I'm writing my stuff on Sublime Text in a template file, and then I push them to the server with a FTP client.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is no JavaScript (nor jQuery), no plugin, no PHP and no database. Only a tiny little stylesheet. Which means the site is fast, and it matters a lot to me, especially when it comes to mobile browsing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I'd like to be able to manage things a little better. For example, I'd like to write my articles in &lt;a href=&quot;http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/syntax&quot; title=&quot;Markdown&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; instead of regular HTML. Also, depending on either I post a lot of code snippets or not I may want to add &lt;a href=&quot;http://prismjs.com/&quot; title=&quot;Prism&quot;&gt;Prism.js&lt;/a&gt; for the syntax highlighting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm currently documenting myself on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki&quot; title=&quot;Jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; to be able to get rid of the FTP client and manage everything on an upper level, but it will take some time before I make the switch.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;About the design&lt;a href=&quot;#design&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I know this may look a little flat but I wanted it to be. It's minimalist to focus on the content and nothing else. No fancy buttons, no complex multi-columns layout, no heavy CSS transitions, etc. It's a blog made with the content, for the content. This is why the font-size is huge, the line-height is important, there is a lot of space, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But I may improve the design over the time of course. :)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id=&quot;to-do&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What's next?&lt;a href=&quot;#to-do&quot; class=&quot;section-anchor&quot;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Honestly I don't know. Blogging when I have time and things to say. Maybe a contact page or something.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For now, I'm not planning on adding a comments system because I don't think there is much need for it. Most people won't take the time to comment anyway, and those who would do can still catch me on &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/hugoGiraudel&quot; title=&quot;Twitter&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;. But if one day I feel like I should allow users to comment, I may think about &lt;a href=&quot;http://disqus.com/&quot; title=&quot;Disqus&quot;&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt;. Mainly because I don't want to spend hours doing PHP stuff on this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, if you find any bug or have any suggestion, please catch me on GTalk or Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 09 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/11/09/redesign-blog/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/11/09/redesign-blog/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>Heading set styling with CSS</title>
				<description>
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 02 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/11/02/codrops-headings/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/11/02/codrops-headings/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>Kick-start your project: a collection of handy CSS snippets</title>
				<description>
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 25 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/10/25/codrops-css-snippets/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/10/25/codrops-css-snippets/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>Basic ready-to-use CSS styles</title>
				<description>
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/10/23/codrops-basic-css/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/10/23/codrops-basic-css/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>Custom login form styling</title>
				<description>
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/10/16/codrops-login-forms/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/10/16/codrops-login-forms/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>Custom drop-down list styling</title>
				<description>
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 04 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/10/04/codrops-drop-down/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/10/04/codrops-drop-down/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
			
			<item>
				<title>Button switches with checkboxes and CSS3 fanciness</title>
				<description>
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/09/13/codrops-buttons/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://hugogiraudel.com/2012/09/13/codrops-buttons/</guid>
			</item>
			
		
	</channel>
</rss>